<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Bio HL Notes]]></title><description><![CDATA[Obsidian digital garden]]></description><link>http://github.com/dylang/node-rss</link><image><url>lib\media\favicon.png</url><title>Bio HL Notes</title><link></link></image><generator>Webpage HTML Export plugin for Obsidian</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 07:54:58 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="lib\rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 07:54:01 GMT</pubDate><ttl>60</ttl><dc:creator></dc:creator><item><title><![CDATA[Ammonia and Nitrification]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>The balance of fish waste being used to supply plants with nutrient.<br><br>Fish produce ammonia, high in nitrogen, but not in a form that is usable by plants.<br><br>Nitrosomonas: ammonia to nitrate<br>
Nitrobacter: nitrate to nitrate<br><br>
<br>Water Conservation,
<br>Higher Yield, 

<br>More product per space,
<br>Faster growth,

<br>(Lettuce takes 6-8 weeks in ideal conditions, can make 100 heads a week here in school.)




<br>Organic Produce, (Less pesticide use)
<br>Quality and Taste, (Tend to be stronger growth, fresh)
<br>Source of Protein, (Fish can be eaten :( )
<br>No Weeds or Soil Pathogens, (only stuff you plant grows.)
<br>Environmentally Friendly, (Less waste)
<br>Decentralized. (Local produce, no need for transport, so no wastage)
<br><br>
<br>Upfront infrastructure costs, (lots of stuff to make)
<br>Learning Curve, (A lot to learn and a lot to mess up)
<br>Multiple Ecosystems = Multiple points of failure. (Hard to keep everything in line)
<br>Consistent electricity. (Things need constant pumping and fans)
<br>Niche market (not everyone might want it)
<br>Less community
<br><br><br>
<br>Mostly freshwater,
<br>Large volumes of water store heat,
<br>High stocking density (how many per space) requires constant aeration,
<br>Fish species selected based on tolerance to bad environments.
<br>Popular fish are Tilapia, Carp, Catfish, Bass, Goldfish and Coy. We have coy.<br><img alt="Image of the Pond.png" src="\aquaponics\aquaponics-images\image-of-the-pond.png" style="width: 300px; max-width: 100%;"><br><br>
<br>Remove solids, (chunks)
<br>Multiple types. (Radial filters, for example,)
<br>Seen below is a swirl filter, slowing speed of water movement down, allowing for clumps to gather at the bottom of the container.<br><img alt="Image of the filter.png" src="\aquaponics\aquaponics-images\image-of-the-filter.png" style="width: 300px; max-width: 100%;"><br><br>
<br>Bacteria is the "engine".
<br>Converts ammonia to nitrate for plants
<br>Bacteria grows on the rocks and solid surfaces in the system,
<br>Needs oxygen.
<br><img alt="Image of the bacteria grow surface.png" src="\aquaponics\aquaponics-images\image-of-the-bacteria-grow-surface.png" style="width: 300px; max-width: 100%;"><br><br>
<br>Stuff to grow crops in.
<br>Basically though, you just need enough plants to clean water for fish.
<br>we have 3 different types of grow beds, <br><img alt="Image of Grow Beds 4.png" src="\aquaponics\aquaponics-images\image-of-grow-beds-4.png" style="width: 150px; max-width: 100%;"> <img alt="Image of Grow Beds 1.png" src="\aquaponics\aquaponics-images\image-of-grow-beds-1.png" style="width: 150px; max-width: 100%;"> <img alt="Image of Grow Beds 2.png" src="\aquaponics\aquaponics-images\image-of-grow-beds-2.png" style="width: 150px; max-width: 100%;"> <img alt="Image of Grow Beds 3.png" src="\aquaponics\aquaponics-images\image-of-grow-beds-3.png" style="width: 150px; max-width: 100%;"> <br><br>
<br>Lowest point in the system,
<br>In the school, it just goes back to the pond,
]]></description><link>aquaponics\session-1.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Aquaponics/Session 1.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 10:02:50 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="aquaponics\aquaponics-images\image-of-the-pond.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;aquaponics\aquaponics-images\image-of-the-pond.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Considerations for Aquaponics Systems - Fish]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br> Aquaponics systems are not meant to be an ideal space for fish; they are stressful and unclean to optimize for nutrient availability for plants. Thus, resilient fish are best suited for aquaponics systems. <br><br><br>The fish you choose to keep should match your crop. (I.E If your crop needs a colder climate, use fish that would live in cold waters.)<br>Male fish are aggressive during mating. Males and females can be mixed in one pool, but only below 23 degrees Celsius, otherwise they mate. Coincidentally, plants tend to prefer that temperature, too.<br>Gills can be used to feed, breath and maintain homeostasis.<br><br>You can only increase density till a certain point, after which stress and disease increases too much and any denser is counterproductive.<br>The most important for the fish is to filter. Food availability and temperature will vary in natural environments, so they can weather you forgetting to feed them or the temperature changing some amount, but filtering is important. <br>Fish have a "Photoperiod", they sense day and nighttime. From this, they know when to sleep, and when to be active. They will not only well- not be able to see food in the water if it is dark, but they also won't want to eat, because to them it's bedtime. Generally, fish area also less aggressive in the shade, so some amount of constant shading is for the best.<br><br>They are basically a form of bioreactor, converting fish food, to ammonia. With this though, means that and incorrect pH or temperature will slow down their output. (I.E. they will stop eating and pooping as much)<br>Optimal temperature tends to be 23-24 Celsius for growth and activity. (Cold water traps more oxygen)<br>Just like people, a fish's rate of metabolism slows then as they age, so it's best to 'remove' them once they get older.<br><br>As a general rule, you're gonna wanna feed the fish approximately:<br>
40g fish food / square meter of grow space / day.<br>The Feed Conversion Ratio (FCR) is the ratio of the mass of food given to fish, to the amount of weight they gain. This is a statistic most important for people who specifically want to grow the fish.<br>It is important to note how this refers to the dry weight of the food, but the wet weight (I.E. not dehydrated) of the fish.<br>The Feed Efficiency Ratio (FER) is 1/FCR.<br>Using the general rule above, assuming we have 100 squared meters of grow space, we would be feeding the fish 0.4 kg of fish food per day;<br>(0.04 kg feed x 100 square meters of grow space) = 4.0 kg / day<br>So; <br>4 kg x 365 days = 1,460 kg fish feed per year,<br>1460 kg x FER = fish weight increase per year,<br><br>These are the stages of a fish growing;<br>
<img alt="Fish Life Cycles.png" src="\aquaponics\aquaponics-images\fish-life-cycles.png" style="width: 400px; max-width: 100%;"><br>It's best not to introduce the baby fish to bigger ones until they are at least fingerlings, to make sure they don't get eaten.<br>It is best to stagger when you start growing groups of fish, so they are never all too old or too young.<br><br>Material must be Inert. so it isn't releasing chemicals into the water. Do not use copper or zinc. it is toxic to fish.<br>All water should be natural water. No tap water, due to treatments like chlorine, they kill bacteria. Also, not all natural water is the same, for example, well water may have the wrong pH.<br>You should also always have more water handy. Evaporation happens, it must be replaced somehow.<br>Fish tanks should ideally be 3 : 1; diameter : depth. - This is best for collecting sediment in the center<br><br>It's best to have a formulated feed, so you know what is going into the system. Whatever you put in to the system will have on the balances of different nutrients.<br><br>An algal bloom can lead to destruction of the environment needed for the system. Sunlight leads to algal growth.]]></description><link>aquaponics\session-2.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Aquaponics/Session 2.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 09:37:38 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="aquaponics\aquaponics-images\fish-life-cycles.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;aquaponics\aquaponics-images\fish-life-cycles.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[pH]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>For ideal function of all elements, 6-7.5 pH is optimal. (6.8ish is best)<br>WHEN IN DOUBT; DON'T DO ANYTHING. FILTERING IS OKAY THOUGH<br><br>pH is basically the amount of free-floating hydrogen ions. Ammonia picks up a hydrogen ion and converts to ammonium. Too much ammonia will kill the fish.<br><br><br>"Strep" is the most common disease found among tilapia. <br>Symptoms:<br>
<br>Lethargic,
<br>Weak,
<br>Loss of appetite,
<br>May swim erratically,
<br>Red discoloration near fins and tail,
<br>Protruding eyes,
<br>Bumps / Growths.
<br>Solution:<br>
<br>Reduce feeding, 
<br>Cool down water, 
<br>Get them out, 
<br>Salty tank for an hour or two. Salt kills off disease.
<br><br>A parasite that infects the scales and gills of a fish.<br>Symptoms:<br>
<br>Rapid breathing,
<br>Rubbing against walls.
<br>Solution:<br>
<br>Kill off the infected.
<br>Examine fish before / salt cleanse of fish.
<br><br>A bacterial Disease<br>Symptoms:<br>
<br>A bump on the back of the fish,
<br>Weakness,
<br>Loss of appetite, 
<br>Solution:<br>
<br>Kill off the infected.
<br>Examine fish before / salt cleanse of fish.
<br><br><img alt="Fish Diagnosis.png" src="\aquaponics\aquaponics-images\fish-diagnosis.png"><br>Fish don't sell well. Sometime it's more efficient, money-wise, to just say goodbye to the fish.<br><br>Depending on climate, and plants' sensitivity, different levels of control are used. Some cases, less control is okay, in other cases, entirely indoor systems are necessary. Prices range widely on this.<br><br><img alt="Greenhouse Forms.png" src="\aquaponics\aquaponics-images\greenhouse-forms.png"><br>
High tech is more expensive.<br><img alt="Pasted image 20241106151336.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20241106151336.png"><br>
Ventilation maintains CO2 levels, for photosynthesis.<br><img alt="Pasted image 20241106151710.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20241106151710.png"><br>
Example of optimizations for minimizing heating requirement.<br><br>Under high temperatures, plants evaporate water, refilling from roots. If not enough water at roots, or can't refill fast enough, plant wilts and dies.<br>From air movement, the stem of a plant is stimulated to grow stronger as it sways.<br><br><img alt="Pasted image 20241106152753.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20241106152753.png" style="width: 400px; max-width: 100%;"><br>Certain processes in the plant increase pH, others decrease it. If intervening, be careful because it may cause drastic reverse fluctuations.]]></description><link>aquaponics\session-3.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Aquaponics/Session 3.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 10:28:33 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="aquaponics\aquaponics-images\fish-diagnosis.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;aquaponics\aquaponics-images\fish-diagnosis.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[ATP Synthase]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><img alt="ATP Synthase Diagram.png" src="\lib\media\atp-synthase-diagram.png"><br>
(ATP Synthase in cellular respiration)<br>A transmembrane enzyme that conducts the conversion of ADP to ATP, utilizing the kinetic potential energy of a concentration gradient across a membrane. It allows release of the pressure of the gradient, resulting in the enzyme rotating, which it then uses to synthesize ATP using ADP and phosphate ions.]]></description><link>definitions\atp-synthase.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Definitions/ATP Synthase.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Feb 2024 07:23:36 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\atp-synthase-diagram.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\atp-synthase-diagram.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Form]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>An organelle present in plant cells responsible for photosynthesis, thus powering the cell.<br><br><img alt="Structure of Chloroplasts.png" src="\lib\media\structure-of-chloroplasts.png" style="width: 500px; max-width: 100%;"><br>Chloroplasts are surrounded by a double membrane, and are filled with many smaller membrane "pods" to maximize surface area. Chloroplast are usually green, and thus responsible for the color of plant cells.]]></description><link>definitions\chloroplasts.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Definitions/Chloroplasts.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Feb 2024 14:44:14 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\structure-of-chloroplasts.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\structure-of-chloroplasts.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Decarboxylation]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Carbon and oxygen removed in the form of carbon dioxide by an enzyme.]]></description><link>definitions\decarboxylation.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Definitions/Decarboxylation.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 04 Feb 2024 13:02:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Electron Carriers]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Electron carriers go through <a data-href="Oxidation and Reduction Reactions" href="\definitions\oxidation-and-reduction-reactions.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Oxidation and Reduction Reactions</a> to carry electrons through systems.<br>NADP is an electron carrier that is [reduced](Unit 3/Oxidation and Reduction Reactions) to NADPH.]]></description><link>definitions\electron-carriers.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Definitions/Electron Carriers.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Feb 2024 05:47:08 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Lactic acid]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>An acidic liquid which builds up in muscle tissue, signaling- through pain- to an organism that the muscle needs time to repair.]]></description><link>definitions\lactic-acid.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Definitions/Lactic acid.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 13:09:28 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Oxidation and Reduction Reactions]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><img alt="OILRIG Oxidation and Reduction Acronym.png" src="\lib\media\oilrig-oxidation-and-reduction-acronym.png" style="width: 500px; max-width: 100%;"><br>Oxidation and reduction are chemical processes that always occur together. When an electron is lost, it must transfer to another molecule. ADP is reduced to ATP when a potassium atom, along with an electron is added. ATP is then oxidized to ADP when used.<br><img alt="Reduction and Oxidation Diagram.png" src="\lib\media\reduction-and-oxidation-diagram.png">]]></description><link>definitions\oxidation-and-reduction-reactions.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Definitions/Oxidation and Reduction Reactions.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Feb 2024 07:19:14 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\oilrig-oxidation-and-reduction-acronym.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\oilrig-oxidation-and-reduction-acronym.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Phosphorylation]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>The addition of a phosphate molecule to an organic molecule. For many reactions the purpose of phosphorylation is to make the phosphorylated molecule less stable and therefore more likely to react. Phosphorylation is sometimes referred to as activating a molecule.]]></description><link>definitions\phosphorylation.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Definitions/Phosphorylation.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2024 07:23:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Action and Absorption Spectra]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Photosynthetic pigments are molecules that absorb photons of light to excite electrons. <br><br><br>Chlorophyl A and B are a photosynthetic pigments and are always present in chloroplasts. In addition to chlorophyl, chloroplasts have accessory pigments.<br><img alt="Absorbtion Graph of Photosynthetic Pigments.png" src="\lib\media\absorbtion-graph-of-photosynthetic-pigments.png" style="width: 600px; max-width: 100%;"><br>
Each different photosynthetic pigment absorb different wavelengths of light less or more. <br>Carotenoids are an example of accessory photosynthetic pigments, which stand to extend the range of wavelengths of light plants can use to photosynthesize as each photosynthetic pigment will be able to absorb a different range of wavelengths.<br>The graph above is called an absorption graph, and graphs the amount of light absorbed by the molecules for the visible light spectrum.<br><br>Below is an absorption and action spectrum overlayed. The semitransparent graphs are the absorption spectrum of multiple photosynthetic pigments, and the fully colored line (the action spectrum) plots the rate of photosynthesis at different wavelengths of lights.<br>Plants photosynthesize at all other colors other than green, as they hold multiple pigments that are sensitive to multiple points on the color spectrum, demonstrated by the peaks in the absorption spectra.<br><img alt="Absorption Spectrum (Photosynthesis).png" src="\lib\media\absorption-spectrum-(photosynthesis).png">]]></description><link>definitions\photosynthetic-pigments.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Definitions/Photosynthetic Pigments.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2024 09:57:42 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\absorbtion-graph-of-photosynthetic-pigments.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\absorbtion-graph-of-photosynthetic-pigments.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Solute Concentration Terminalogy]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><img alt="Pasted image 20240326115550.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240326115550.png">]]></description><link>definitions\solute-concentration-terminalogy.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Definitions/Solute Concentration Terminalogy.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2024 06:56:03 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\pasted-image-20240326115550.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\pasted-image-20240326115550.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Chi-Squared]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Compares categorical data, to an expected result.<br>Tests against a null hypothesis, a statement that says there is no correlation.]]></description><link>investigation-knowhow\analytical-tests.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Investigation Knowhow/Analytical Tests.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 08:34:31 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[T-Test]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 ]]></description><link>investigation-knowhow\t-test.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Investigation Knowhow/T-Test.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2024 08:27:08 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Accuracy and Precision]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>The accuracy of a measurement is how close it is to being correct. (Find a resource with perfect data.)<br>
The precision of an instrument is how consistent it is. (Use standard deviation.)<br><img alt="Accuracy and Precision.png" src="\lib\media\accuracy-and-precision.png" style="width: 400px; max-width: 100%;"><br><br>ALWAYS talk about your calculations.]]></description><link>investigation-knowhow\uncertainty.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Investigation Knowhow/Uncertainty.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2024 06:02:17 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\accuracy-and-precision.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\accuracy-and-precision.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Red Blood Cells]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Some Eukaryotes do not feature all of the structures in most eukaryotes.<br><br>Red blood cells do not have a nucleus, to optimize it's carrying capacity of oxygen.<br><br>Aseptate fungal hyphae are multinucleate(meaning multiple nuclei share one common cytoplasm) and are not divided up into individual cells.<br><img alt="Pasted image 20240303153203.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240303153203.png"><br><br>Cell walls are missing or highly perforated. No true organelles.<br><img alt="Pasted image 20240303153245.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240303153245.png">]]></description><link>unit-1\atypical-eukaryotes.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 1/Atypical Eukaryotes.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2024 10:32:57 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\pasted-image-20240303153203.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\pasted-image-20240303153203.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Structure of Membranes]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><br>Cell membranes, or plasma membranes are made up of phospholipids, arranged in a phospholipid bilayer.<br><img alt="Pasted image 20240303193953.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240303193953.png"><br>Phospholipids are made of a phosphate head attached to two <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Fatty acids" data-href="Fatty acids" href="\unit-2\fatty-acids.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">fatty acid</a> tails, one of which is unsaturated. The head is hydrophilic (water-loving), whereas the tails are hydrophobic.<br>When phospholipids are mixed with water they become arranged in double layers, with the heads facing outwards and the tails inwards. This arrangement, called a phospholipid bilayer, is the basis of the membranes of cells. <br><img alt="Pasted image 20240303194253.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240303194253.png"><br>Phospholipids and other amphipathic (hydrophilic and hydrophobic) lipids naturally form continuous sheet like bilayers in water.<br>Hydrophobic hydrocarbon chains that form the core of a membrane have low permeability to large molecules and hydrophilic particles, including ions and polar molecules, so membranes function as effective barriers between aqueous solutions.<br><br><br>Cell membranes also have proteins, some of these are embedded, called integral proteins. Others are attached to the surface, called peripheral proteins.<br><br>When sugar or carbohydrate are linked to the lipids in the lipid bilayer, it is called a glycolipid. <br>When sugar or carbohydrates are linked to a membrane protein, it is called a glycoprotein. <br>Both have roles in cell adhesion and cell recognition. <br><br><img alt="Pasted image 20240303194944.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240303194944.png" style="width: 300px; max-width: 100%;"><br>
Only animal cell plasma membranes contain cholesterol. Cholesterol molecules in membranes reduce membrane fluidity and therefore permeability to small water-soluble molecules. Without cholesterol (such as in a bacterium) a cell would need a cell wall. <br><br><img alt="Pasted image 20240303195019.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240303195019.png"><br>Cell membranes are a fluid structure, constantly rearranging and shifting around its molecules. This allows for water and small molecules dissolved in water to pass through the membrane.<br>One of the tails of phospholipids is unsaturated as it allows for the phospholipids to space themselves out, promoting fluidity. <br>Cholesterol regulates fluidity of the membrane. At high temperatures, cholesterol's flat, rigid structure limits phospholipid movement. <br>At low temperatures, however, cholesterol has the opposite effect: By&nbsp;interfering with interactions between fatty acid chains, cholesterol prevents membranes from freezing and maintains membrane fluidity.]]></description><link>unit-1\cell-membranes.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 1/Cell Membranes.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2024 16:15:40 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\pasted-image-20240303193953.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\pasted-image-20240303193953.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Cell Specialization]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>An adult human body contains a wide array of different cell types, from nerve cells to liver cells to blood cells. Each of these cell types have a specific function, and are only found in specific areas of the body, in certain tissues or certain organs, wherever their function is needed.<br>These are known as specialized cells.<br><img alt="Pasted image 20240303165420.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240303165420.png" style="width: 500px; max-width: 100%;"><br><br><img alt="Pasted image 20240303165441.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240303165441.png" style="width: 500px; max-width: 100%;"><br>Stem cells are sort of like "mother cells" that can form any cell in our body.<br><br>Stem cells usually become more and more restricted in their potential as development of the embryo progresses. Stem cells can be classified by the extent to which they can differentiate into different cell types. These four main classifications are&nbsp;totipotent, pluripotent, multipotent, or unipotent.<br>
<img alt="Pasted image 20240303165701.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240303165701.png" style="width: 500px; max-width: 100%;"><br><img alt="Pasted image 20240303165555.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240303165555.png" style="width: 500px; max-width: 100%;"><br><br><img alt="Pasted image 20240303165614.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240303165614.png"><br>Stem cells can function as a usual cell would, but can self renew, or differentiate into another, mature cell.<br><br>The microenvironment where stem cells reside in adults is considered a niche. The niche should not only be considered as a physical location but also a place where chemical stimuli influence stem cell behavior.<br><br><img alt="Kidney_Niche (1).png" src="\lib\media\kidney_niche-(1).png">]]></description><link>unit-1\cell-specialization.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 1/Cell Specialization.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2024 12:00:23 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\pasted-image-20240303165420.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\pasted-image-20240303165420.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Cell Theory]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Formed from Robert Hooke’s 1665 observations of cork cells. (Meaning literally cells extracted from corks).<br><br>
<br>
All living organisms are composed of cells<br>
Although the smallest organisms may consist of one cell only

<br>
Cells are the smallest unit of life<br>
Nothing smaller can survive independently

<br>
Cells come from pre-existing cells<br>
by cell division – and therefore new cells cannot be constructed from non-living chemical substances.

<br><br>All living organisms carry out the 7 functions of life. (A good acronym to remember them is Ms.GrenHM)<br><a data-href="Metabolism" href="\unit-2\metabolism.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Metabolism</a><br>
Essentially, the sum of all the enzyme-catalyzed chemical reactions taking place in the organism. (The breaking down and and formation of compounds within the organism done pointedly.)<br>Sensitivity<br>
The organism to sense and react to changes in it's environment.<br>Growth<br>
An irreversible increase in size.<br>Reproduction<br>
The production of offspring. (Sexually or asexually.)<br>Excretion<br>
Excretion of metabolic waste from the organism.<br>Nourishment<br>
Obtaining food to provide energy and materials for other functions of life.<br>Homeostasis<br>
Keeping conditions inside the organism within tolerable limits <br>Movement<br>
The process of moving your body/a body part from one position to another]]></description><link>unit-1\cell-theory-and-functions-of-life.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 1/Cell Theory and Functions of Life.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2024 10:09:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Endo and Exocytosis]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>A vesicle is a small sac of membrane with a droplet of fluid inside. Vesicles are usually spherical and are present in most eukaryotic cells. They form from larger pieces of membrane. To form a vesicle, a small region of a membrane is pulled from the rest of the membrane and is pinched off. Proteins in the membrane carry out this process using energy from ATP. <br>Vesicles move materials within cells.<br>The fluidity of membranes also allows them to break or reform during endocytosis and exocytosis.<br><br><img alt="Pasted image 20240303211724.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240303211724.png">]]></description><link>unit-1\endo-and-exocytosis.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 1/Endo and Exocytosis.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2024 16:17:46 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\pasted-image-20240303211724.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\pasted-image-20240303211724.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Endosymbiotic Theory]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Endosymbiotic Theory, in simplest terms explains the origin of eukaryotes from prokaryotes. <br>Large prokaryotes began absorbing smaller prokaryotes, such as mitochondria, and the mitochondria continued functioning as normal inside of the larger prokaryotes, supplying the larger cell with, in the case of the mitochondria, ATP.]]></description><link>unit-1\endosymbiotic-theory.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 1/Endosymbiotic Theory.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2024 10:00:20 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Prokaryotes vs Eukaryotes]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Eukaryotes are like eu and I, cells with smaller organelles within them.<br><br>Eukaryotic cells have a much more complicated compartmentalized internal structure than prokaryotic cells. They have a nucleus and organelles in the cytoplasm with single or double membranes. Each organelle has a distinctive structure and function.<br><br><br>All 3 are eukaryotic, fungi is somewhat an outlier.<br>]]></description><link>unit-1\eukaryotes.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 1/Eukaryotes.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2024 10:28:04 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Simple Diffusion and Osmosis]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Particles move across membranes by simple diffusion, osmosis, facilitated diffusion and active transport.<br><br>In simple diffusion, some particles simply make their way though the gaps between the phospholipids in the membrane. <br><img alt="Pasted image 20240303210845.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240303210845.png"><br><br>An aquaporin, also called a water channel, is a transmembrane protein that allows the passage of water molecules through the cell membrane (osmosis). They are not present in all cell membranes.<br><br>Channels are made between a single protein molecule or between a group of proteins filter and let through specific particles by limiting the size, shape and charge of said particles.<br><img alt="Pasted image 20240303211159.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240303211159.png"><br><br>Transporting molecules cross membranes, against the concentration gradient, using pump proteins. This requires the <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Oxidation and Reduction Reactions" data-href="Oxidation and Reduction Reactions" href="\definitions\oxidation-and-reduction-reactions.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">oxidation</a> of ATP to ADP.<br><img alt="Pasted image 20240303211254.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240303211254.png" style="width: 300px; max-width: 100%;">]]></description><link>unit-1\membrane-transport.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 1/Membrane Transport.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2024 16:14:06 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\pasted-image-20240303210845.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\pasted-image-20240303210845.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Cell wall]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>A wall surrounding a cell. Typically made of complex polysaccharides such as&nbsp;chitin, glucans, and glycoproteins in fungi, or cellulose in plants. Used to provide structural support, protection, and maintaining water levels. Inhibits plants from absorbing hard foods.<br><br>Also known as the phospholipid bilayer is a membrane surrounding all cells, made of phospholipids. This is a complex topic, more can be read <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="." target="_blank">here</a>.<br><br>A water-based liquid which fills all cells. All metabolic processes take place within it.<br><br>A free-flowing strand of DNA in a loop, not contained. <br><br>Molecular machines that produce proteins from amino acids during protein synthesis. There are 2 common sizes 70S and 80S. (S = Svedberg units, a measure of the size of organelles) They appear in prokaryotes and eukaryotes respectively.<br><br>A compartment with a double membrane, which contains chromosomes, made of DNA bound to histones contained in a double membrane with pores.<br><br>A smaller sack of liquid bound by a membrane within cells. Plant and fungal cells often have a permanent one. <br>Animal cells will feature them when necessary for metabolism and a lack of a large vacuole reduces the mass of the cell and makes movement easier, so animals have much greater range of locomotion methods e.g. flying.<br>Often the largest organelle in fungi. The vacuole participates in a wide range of processes and play a key role in the regulation of cellular homeostasis.<br>In plant cells it contains a solution of mineral ions such as potassium and other solutes.<br>
The vacuole can expand quickly by absorbing mineral ions and water and therefore allows rapid growth of plant cells.<br><br> Chloroplasts<br><br>An organelle present in plant cells responsible for photosynthesis, thus powering the cell.<br><br><img alt="Structure of Chloroplasts.png" src="\lib\media\structure-of-chloroplasts.png" style="width: 500px; max-width: 100%;"><br>Chloroplasts are surrounded by a double membrane, and are filled with many smaller membrane "pods" to maximize surface area. Chloroplast are usually green, and thus responsible for the color of plant cells.<br><br>Mitochondria are surrounded by a double membrane, and are filled with folds to maximize surface area. They conduct <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Cellular Respiration" data-href="Cellular Respiration" href="\unit-3\cellular-respiration.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">cellular respiration</a>, utilizing sugar and oxygen to <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Oxidation and Reduction Reactions" data-href="Oxidation and Reduction Reactions" href="\definitions\oxidation-and-reduction-reactions.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">reduce</a> ATP.<br><br>The endoplasmic reticulum transpires in two forms: a type with a ribosome-studded surface and another with a smooth surface. The latter is called the smooth endoplasmic reticulum, and the former is called the rough endoplasmic reticulum. These membranes form continuous folds, eventually joining the outer layer of the nuclear membrane. <br><br>
<br>Synthesis of essential lipids such as phospholipids and cholesterol. 
<br>Production and secretion of steroid hormones.
<br>Metabolism of carbohydrates.
<br>Store and releases calcium ions. (Important for the nervous system and muscular systems.)
<br><br>
<br>Mainly protein synthesis using the embedded ribosomes. 
<br>Protein folding. (Forming a 3D protein from a string of amino acids)
<br>Protein sorting. 
<br><br>Its main function is the packaging and secretion of proteins. It receives proteins from Endoplasmic Reticulum. It packages it into membrane-bound vesicles, which are then transported to various destinations, such as lysosomes, plasma membrane or secretion. They also take part in the transport of lipids and the formation of lysosomes.<br><br>A complex mesh of protein filaments and motor proteins. Provides shape and support to the cell, organizes the organelles.]]></description><link>unit-1\organelles-and-features-of-cells.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 1/Organelles and Features of Cells.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2024 07:29:06 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\structure-of-chloroplasts.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\structure-of-chloroplasts.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Unicellular Organisms]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Organisms consisting of only one cell that carry out all functions of life.<br><br><img alt="Pasted image 20240218123059.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240218123059.png"><br>An example of a unicellular organism is Paramecium. The diagram below briefly summarizes how it carries out the 8 functions of life.<br><img alt="Pasted image 20240218161944.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240218161944.png"><br><br>Prokaryotes were the first organisms to evolve on Earth and they still have the simplest cell structures without compartmentalization. Bacteria are prokaryotes. They are mostly small in size, unicellular and are found almost everywhere – in soil, in water, on our skin, in our intestines and even in the pools of hot water in volcanic soils.<br><br>Bacteria are highly successful organisms:<br>
<br>They survive in a huge variety of habitats
<br>They have many strategies for obtaining food/energy
<br>They reproduce very quickly
<br>There a 3 types of bacteria:<br>Photosynthetic, chemosynthetic and parasitic, which rely on light energy, chemical energy and the life force of another being, respectively.<br><br><img alt="Pasted image 20240218165127.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240218165127.png" style="width: 500px; max-width: 100%;"><br>While the structure and features of cell will vary for life in different environments, all prokaryotes have a <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Organelles and Features of Cells > Cell wall" data-href="Organelles and Features of Cells#Cell wall" href="\unit-1\organelles-and-features-of-cells.html#Cell_wall" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">cell wall</a>, <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Organelles and Features of Cells > Plasma membrane" data-href="Organelles and Features of Cells#Plasma membrane" href="\unit-1\organelles-and-features-of-cells.html#Plasma_membrane" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">plasma membrane</a>, <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Organelles and Features of Cells > Cytoplasm" data-href="Organelles and Features of Cells#Cytoplasm" href="\unit-1\organelles-and-features-of-cells.html#Cytoplasm" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">cytoplasm</a>, <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Organelles and Features of Cells > Ribosomes" data-href="Organelles and Features of Cells#Ribosomes" href="\unit-1\organelles-and-features-of-cells.html#Ribosomes" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">70S ribosomes</a>, and <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Organelles and Features of Cells > Naked DNA" data-href="Organelles and Features of Cells#Naked DNA" href="\unit-1\organelles-and-features-of-cells.html#Naked_DNA" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">naked DNA</a>.]]></description><link>unit-1\prokaryotes.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 1/Prokaryotes.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2024 15:54:56 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\pasted-image-20240218123059.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\pasted-image-20240218123059.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Unit 1 Study Guide]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>A2.2.1 Cells are the basic structural unit of all living organisms<br>
A2.2.4 There are structures common to all cells in all living organisms<br>
A2.2.7 Processes of life in unicellular organisms include homeostasis, metabolism, nutrition, movement, excretion, growth, response to stimuli and reproduction.<br>
A2.2.5 Students must learn prokaryote cell structure including: cell wall, plasma membrane, cytoplasm, naked DNA in a loop and 70S ribosomes. Students should also appreciate that prokaryote cell structure varies.<br>
A2.2.6 Students should be familiar with features common to eukaryotic cells:<br>
• a plasma membrane enclosing a compartmentalized cytoplasm with 80S ribosomes<br>
• a nucleus with chromosomes made of DNA bound to histones contained in a double membrane with pores<br>
• membrane-bound cytoplasmic organelles including mitochondria, endoplasmic reticulum, Golgi apparatus, and a variety of vesicles or vacuoles including lysosomes<br>
• a cytoskeleton of microtubules and microfilaments<br>
A2.2.8 Identify the differences in eukaryotic cell structure between animals, fungi and plants<br>
A2.2.9 Students must understand that certain eukaryotic cells have an atypical cell structure, and be able to name examples.<br>
A2.2.10 Cell types and cell structures viewed in light and electron<br>
A2.2.11 Drawing and annotation based on electron micrographs<br>
A2.2.14 Multicellularity has the advantage of allowing larger body size and cell specialization.<br>
A2.2.13 Cell differentiation is the process for developing specialized tissues in multicellular organisms<br>
A2.2.12 Origin of eukaryotic cells by endosymbiosis<br>Organelles, Eu vs Pro, magni, transport.]]></description><link>unit-1\unit-1-study-guide.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 1/Unit 1 Study Guide.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Feb 2024 07:25:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Polarity and Hydrogen Bonds]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><img alt="Pasted image 20240226110535.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240226110535.png"><br>Water is the main component of living things, it provides the environment in which the biochemical reactions of life can occur and takes part in and is produced by many reactions. <br><br>It is a polar molecule. The covalent bond between hydrogen and oxygen involves the unequal sharing of electrons giving the molecule an unequal charge distribution. <br>The polarity causes hydrogen to be slightly positive and oxygen to be slightly negative. The result is that water molecules tend to stick together because of the formation of hydrogen bonds.<br><br>Hydrogen bonds are not actual bonds but an interaction between molecules; it does not change the chemical properties of the molecule and is significantly weaker than a covalent or ionic bond.<br><br>Hydrogen bonds hold a mass of water together to some extent. This is known as cohesion. Surface tension is an example of cohesion<br>Water tends to be attracted to the walls of it's container. This is known as adhesion.<br>Cohesion and Adhesion are useful in transporting nutrients up the stem of a plant.<br><br>A large amount of energy is needed to break the many weak hydrogen bonds between water molecules. This gives water a high specific heat capacity. <br>The thermal properties of water allow it to keep an organism’s temperature fairly constant. <br>A major component of blood it carries heat from warmer parts of the body to cooler ones. <br>In order for water to evaporate, many hydrogen bonds must be broken, so evaporation requires a lot of energy and and takes a great deal of heat with it.<br><br>Water is known as a universal solvent. Its polarity makes it an excellent solvent for other polar molecules. <br>The solvent properties of water also make it an excellent medium for transporting substances around the bodies of all organisms. In plants, the xylem carries dissolved minerals from the roots to the leaves, while the phloem transports soluble sugars up and down the plant. Many animals have blood as their transport medium. Blood is predominantly water, and the blood plasma carries many dissolved solutes including amino acids, glucose, cholesterol, fats, sodium chloride and carbon dioxide. <br><br>]]></description><link>unit-1\water.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 1/Water.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2024 08:42:27 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\pasted-image-20240226110535.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\pasted-image-20240226110535.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Bonds]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a class="tag" href="?query=tag:BIOUnit1" style="background-color: rgb(4, 108, 116); color: white; font-weight: 700; border: none; border-radius: 1em; padding: 0.2em 0.5em;">#BIOUnit1</a> 
 <br><img alt="Covalent Vs Ionic Bonds.png" src="\lib\media\covalent-vs-ionic-bonds.png" style="width: 300px; max-width: 100%;"><br><br>Bonds that share the electrons between two atoms.<br><br>Bonds where electrons are transferred and charge keeps the atoms together.<br>
<a href=".?query=tag:BIOUnit1" class="tag" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow">#BIOUnit1</a>]]></description><link>unit-2\bonds.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 2/Bonds.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 09:37:02 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\covalent-vs-ionic-bonds.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\covalent-vs-ionic-bonds.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Common Carbohydrates]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a class="tag" href="?query=tag:BIOUnit1" style="background-color: rgb(4, 108, 116); color: white; font-weight: 700; border: none; border-radius: 1em; padding: 0.2em 0.5em;">#BIOUnit1</a> 
 <br>Carbohydrate are produced by linking together monosaccharide monomers to build disaccharide and polysaccharide polymers using a glycosidic bond. <br>This is a condensation reaction (H2O released)<br><br><br><a href=".?query=tag:BIOUnit1" class="tag" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow">#BIOUnit1</a>]]></description><link>unit-2\carbohydrates.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 2/Carbohydrates.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Feb 2024 07:03:27 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Carbon]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a class="tag" href="?query=tag:BIOUnit1" style="background-color: rgb(4, 108, 116); color: white; font-weight: 700; border: none; border-radius: 1em; padding: 0.2em 0.5em;">#BIOUnit1</a> 
 <br>All organic molecules contain two or more atoms of carbon. Carbon atoms easily bond to each other and can form four single covalent bonds, or a fewer combination of single and double bonds with other atoms, allowing a diversity of stable compounds to exist.<br>
<a href=".?query=tag:BIOUnit1" class="tag" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow">#BIOUnit1</a>]]></description><link>unit-2\carbon.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 2/Carbon.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 09:37:29 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Elements found in living organisms]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a class="tag" href="?query=tag:BIOUnit1" style="background-color: rgb(4, 108, 116); color: white; font-weight: 700; border: none; border-radius: 1em; padding: 0.2em 0.5em;">#BIOUnit1</a> 
 <br>Carbon, hydrogen, oxygen and nitrogen are the four most common elements found in living organisms. (CHON)<br>Carbon, hydrogen and oxygen are found in all the key organic molecules: proteins, carbohydrates, nucleic acids and lipids. Proteins and nucleic acids also contain nitrogen.<br>Any compound that does not contain carbon is said to be inorganic. A variety of inorganic substances are found in living things and are vital to both the structure and functioning of different organisms. <br><br><br><a href=".?query=tag:BIOUnit1" class="tag" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow">#BIOUnit1</a>]]></description><link>unit-2\elements-found-in-living-organisms.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 2/Elements found in living organisms.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 09:37:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Enzyme function]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a class="tag" href="?query=tag:BIOUnit1" style="background-color: rgb(4, 108, 116); color: white; font-weight: 700; border: none; border-radius: 1em; padding: 0.2em 0.5em;">#BIOUnit1</a> 
 <br>Enzymes are a type of protein that are natural catalysts. Catalysts are molecules that increase the rate of reaction between two other molecules without being altered themselves. <br><br>An enzyme functions by allowing for one of the substrates involved in a reaction to bond with the active site of an enzyme, thus reducing weakening the rest of the substrate's bonds and lowering the activation energy required for the second substrate to react with the first.<br><br>Different enzymes can only bond with to different, specific sets of substrates, this is known as enzyme-substrate specificity. The form of an enzyme is such that it can only bond with the substrate. The enzyme can, however, mold around a substrate somewhat. Much like a glove stretches and molds around a hand, so can an enzyme.<br><img alt="Induced-Fit Model.png" src="\lib\media\induced-fit-model.png"><br><br><img alt="Efficiency Of Enzymes Factors.png" src="\lib\media\efficiency-of-enzymes-factors.png"><br><br>As enzymes are proteins, if the pH of it's environment is too low or too high, they will begin to denature, thus losing effectiveness<br><br>Similarly to pH, if the temperature in the environment of an enzyme is too high, it will begin to denature. However, low temperatures do not denature the enzyme, only reduce the number and strength of collisions in the substance, and thus the likelihood of a collision with enough kinetic energy to match the activation energy of the reaction.<br><br>Simply put, a higher substrate concentration means a greater chance there is a substrate in each enzyme, however, given a high enough concentration, all enzymes in the solution will be occupied, thus further increase in concentration would have no effect.<br><br>Enzyme inhibition refers to when an molecule (inhibitor) interacts with an enzyme in order to stall it's function.<br><br>Competitive inhibitors are molecules that have the right form and charge to bond with the active site of an enzyme, however, do not react with the substrate, thus blocking the correct substrate from bonding with the active site. If the substrate concentration increases in the environment of the enzyme however, the inhibitor will be expelled from the active site, and enzyme function will resume as normal.<br><br>Non-competitive inhibitors work by bonding to another part of the enzyme, not the active site, and altering the enzyme's form by breaking it's bonds, thus stopping it from working. Unlike competitive inhibitors, this process is not reversable.<br>
<a href=".?query=tag:BIOUnit1" class="tag" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow">#BIOUnit1</a>]]></description><link>unit-2\enzymes.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 2/Enzymes.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 09:37:41 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\induced-fit-model.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\induced-fit-model.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Fatty acids]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a class="tag" href="?query=tag:BIOUnit1" style="background-color: rgb(4, 108, 116); color: white; font-weight: 700; border: none; border-radius: 1em; padding: 0.2em 0.5em;">#BIOUnit1</a> 
 <br>Fatty acids consist of a long chain of carbon atoms that are joined to hydrogen atoms. If the carbon chain is linked to the maximum number of H atoms with no double bonds it is saturated, because no more H atoms can be added. The length of a fatty acid can vary<br><img alt="Saturated Fatty Acid Diagram.png" src="\lib\media\saturated-fatty-acid-diagram.png" style="width: 700px; max-width: 100%;"><br>If the chain contains a double bond between two of the carbon atoms it is unsaturated.<br>A chain with just one double bond is monounsaturated, while one with two or more double bonds is polyunsaturated.<br>Polyunsaturated fatty acids tend to be liquids at room temperature and are mainly from plant sources, e.g. sunflower oil and olive oil.<br><img alt="Cis and Trans Unsaturated Fatty Acids.png" src="\lib\media\cis-and-trans-unsaturated-fatty-acids.png" style="width: 700px; max-width: 100%;"><br>Unsaturated fatty acids may be either cis or trans configuration. If the spaces where additional hydrogen atoms could bond are both on the same side of the fatty acid it is known as a cis fatty acid and the carbon chain is slightly bent. If the spaces are on opposite sides, it is a trans fatty acid, which has a straight chain.<br><br>Trans fatty acids and saturated fatty acids when overconsumed can cause CHD due to it depositing in arteries.<br>
<a href=".?query=tag:BIOUnit1" class="tag" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow">#BIOUnit1</a>]]></description><link>unit-2\fatty-acids.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 2/Fatty acids.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Feb 2024 07:25:43 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\saturated-fatty-acid-diagram.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\saturated-fatty-acid-diagram.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Key Properties of Lipids]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a class="tag" href="?query=tag:BIOUnit1" style="background-color: rgb(4, 108, 116); color: white; font-weight: 700; border: none; border-radius: 1em; padding: 0.2em 0.5em;">#BIOUnit1</a> 
 <br><br><br><br> Fats and oils, or triglyceride lipids, are compounds of glycerol and fatty acids, formed by linking 3 or more fatty acids and one glycerol in a condensation reaction. Glycerol has just one structural form but fatty acids have a wide variety of structures, which give the lipids that contain them their different physical and chemical properties. <br> They are fats if they are solid at room temperature or oils if they are liquid at room temperature. Animals store energy as fat whereas plants store oils, for example, olive oil. <br><br> Other types of lipids include steroids, that act as hormones, waxes, that serve as hydrophobic barriers on the upper surface of leaves, and fatty acids that serve as structural components of cell membranes.<br>
<a href=".?query=tag:BIOUnit1" class="tag" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow">#BIOUnit1</a>]]></description><link>unit-2\lipids.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 2/Lipids.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 09:37:47 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Metabolic Pathways]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a class="tag" href="?query=tag:BIOUnit1" style="background-color: rgb(4, 108, 116); color: white; font-weight: 700; border: none; border-radius: 1em; padding: 0.2em 0.5em;">#BIOUnit1</a> 
 <br>Metabolism is the sum of all the enzyme-catalyzed chemical reactions that occur in a living organism. In anabolic reactions complex organic molecules are build from simpler ones using energy, for example photosynthesis. In catabolic reactions complex organic molecules are broken down with the release of energy, for example cellular respiration.<br>Metabolism = anabolism + catabolism.<br><br>Metabolism consists of chains and/or cycles of enzyme-catalyzed reactions. These reactions occur in specific sequences and are called metabolic pathways. The specificity of enzymes means that a reaction only occurs in the presence of a specific enzyme.<br><img alt="Metabolic Pathway.png" src="\lib\media\metabolic-pathway.png" style="width: 400px; max-width: 100%;"><br><br>Sometimes, the final product in a metabolic pathway will act as an inhibitor for the first enzyme, meaning that if the concentration of the end product in the pathway's environment increases, the pathway will shut down, until the concentration decreases once more, allowing for homeostasis, and avoiding over-production of the final product.<br>
<a href=".?query=tag:BIOUnit1" class="tag" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow">#BIOUnit1</a>]]></description><link>unit-2\metabolism.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 2/Metabolism.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 09:37:55 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\metabolic-pathway.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\metabolic-pathway.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Condensation and Hydrolysis]]></title><description><![CDATA[<a class="tag" href="?query=tag:BIOUnit1" style="background-color: rgb(4, 108, 116); color: white; font-weight: 700; border: none; border-radius: 1em; padding: 0.2em 0.5em;">#BIOUnit1</a> 
 <br>Life is based on carbon compounds, that seem complex, but are all just made from smaller divisions (monomers), that then link together to form polymers. <br><br><br>Parts of Metabolism. thus enzyme-catalyzed. Condensation is an anabolic reaction. During condensation an H2O molecule is released and two monomers are joined with a strong covalent bond. Reversely, during Hydrolysis, a catabolic reaction, H2O molecule is split and replaced into two monomers, broken down from a polymer. Hydrolysis takes place during digestion. <br><img alt="Peptide bonds.png" src="\lib\media\peptide-bonds.png" style="width: 300px; max-width: 100%;"><br><br><a href=".?query=tag:BIOUnit1" class="tag" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow">#BIOUnit1</a>]]></description><link>unit-2\natural-polymers.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 2/Natural Polymers.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 09:38:01 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\peptide-bonds.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\peptide-bonds.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Amino Acids]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><img alt="Amino Acid.png" src="\lib\media\amino-acid.png" style="width: 300px; max-width: 100%;"><br>The smallest units(monomers) of a protein, feature an amino and carboxyl group, connected by R-C-H. "R" is a variable that can be different atoms.<br><br>A polypeptide is the primary structure of a protein. The sequence of the amino acids within a polypeptide is determined by genetic code.<br>Polypeptides are polymers built of amino acid monomers during a condensation reaction. The amino group, (NH2) of one amino acids, and the carboxyl group (COOH) of another form a peptide bond, forming a dipeptide. This can continue to from a string of amino acids, called a polypeptide. <br><br>A polypeptide becomes a protein when it folds and connects to itself, or to other polypeptides.<br>Primary structure<br>
Amino acids form a sequence, known as a polypeptide.<br>Secondary structure (Now a protein)<br>
The polypeptide beings to coil up and bond with itself through hydrogen bonds.<br>Tertiary (3rd Level) Structure<br>
Secondary structures fold over once more and Ionic bonds and disulfide bridges form. <br>Quaternary (4th Level) Structure<br>
Quaternary structures are composed of two or more linked polypeptides.<br><img alt="Levels Of Protein Structure.png" src="\lib\media\levels-of-protein-structure.png" style="width: 300px; max-width: 100%;"><br><br>The function of a protein is determined by the shape of its molecule. Proteins are divided into two main types: globular and fibrous proteins.<br><br><br>Denaturation is an irreversible process when a protein loses it's form due to a PH or Temperature outside it's operating range. The primary structure of the protein will usually remain but secondary, tertiary and quaternary structures are usually lost.<br>For example enzymes, which are tertiary proteins, are easily denatured by extremes of pH or temperature and lose the ability to function as catalysts.  <br><img alt="A fresh egg with clear albumin protein and a cooked egg where the albumin has been denatured.png" src="\lib\media\a-fresh-egg-with-clear-albumin-protein-and-a-cooked-egg-where-the-albumin-has-been-denatured.png" style="width: 200px; max-width: 100%;">]]></description><link>unit-2\proteins.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 2/Proteins.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2024 17:15:39 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\amino-acid.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\amino-acid.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Using carbohydrates and lipids in energy storage]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>]]></description><link>unit-2\using-carbohydrates-and-lipids-in-energy-storage.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 2/Using carbohydrates and lipids in energy storage.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 27 Feb 2024 07:12:44 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Mock IA]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 ]]></description><link>unit-3\tasks\mock-ia.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 3/Tasks/Mock IA.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 07:05:17 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Form and Function of the Mitochondria]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><img alt="Labeled Mitochondria Structural Diagram.png" src="\lib\media\labeled-mitochondria-structural-diagram.png"><br>
The structure of the mitochondrion is adapted to the function it performs. <br>CORRECTION : INTERMEMBRANE SPACE "PROTONS ARE PUMPED"<br><br><img alt="Simple Cellular Respiration Diagram.png" src="\lib\media\simple-cellular-respiration-diagram.png"><br><br>Glucose + Oxygen = Carbon Dioxide + Water + ATP<br>C6H12O6 + 6 O2 = 6 CO2 + 6 H2O + ATP<br>The last stage of cellular respiration produces the most ATP and is only possible because of the hydrogen concentration gradient, which, in return only exists due to the function of the ionic pumps powered by the electrons carried from the previous 3 stages.<br><br>There are two electron carriers involved with cellular respiration; NAD and FAD<br><br><img alt="Glycolysis Diagram.png" src="\lib\media\glycolysis-diagram.png" style="width: 300px; max-width: 100%;"><br>
Takes place in the cytoplasm, outside the mitochondria. Glucose is converted to pyruvate. The metabolic pathway in glycolysis is catalyzed by enzymes, which are found in the cytoplasm. <br>Glucose is partially oxidized and a small amount of ATP is produced; partial oxidization is achieved without the use of oxygen.<br>One glucose molecule is converted into two pyruvates. 2 ATP molecules are used but 4 are produced, so there is a net yield of 2 ATP molecules.<br>Two NAD+ are converted into two NADH + H+.<br><br><br>The addition of 2 phosphate groups to a molecule of glucose to form hexose biphosphate, to form an unstable molecule. Converts 2 ATP to ADP in the process.<br><br>The hexose biphosphate splits to 2 triose phosphate due to it's unstable nature.<br><br>Two atoms of hydrogen are removed from each triose phosphate. The energy released by this oxidation is used to link another phosphate group, producing a three carbon compound carrying two phosphate groups. NAD is the hydrogen carrier that accepts the hydrogen atoms.<br><br>Triose Biphosphate is converted to pyruvate, forming 2 ATP from ADP. As this is only half of the reaction it the output totals to 4 ATP.<br><br>Pyruvate travels into the mitochondrial matrix from the cytoplasm.<br>The link reaction essentially prepares the pyruvate for the Krebs cycle.<br>Pyruvate than goes through oxidative decarboxylation, which is the combination of <a data-href="Decarboxylation" href="\definitions\decarboxylation.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Decarboxylation</a> and <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Oxidation and Reduction Reactions" data-href="Oxidation and Reduction Reactions" href="\definitions\oxidation-and-reduction-reactions.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Oxidation</a>, producing an acetyl group, which is accepted by an enzyme in the Krebs cycle.<br>The link reaction involves one decarboxylation and one oxidation. There are two more decarboxylation's and four more oxidations in the Krebs cycle.<br><br><img alt="Krebs Cycle Diagram.png" src="\lib\media\krebs-cycle-diagram.png" style="width: 300px; max-width: 100%;"><br><br><br><a data-href="Decarboxylation" href="\definitions\decarboxylation.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Decarboxylation</a> occurs in two of the reactions, it is a waste product and is excreted along with the CO2 from the link reaction.<br><br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Oxidation and Reduction Reactions" data-href="Oxidation and Reduction Reactions" href="\definitions\oxidation-and-reduction-reactions.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Oxidation</a> occurs and hydrogen is removed in four of the reactions. In three of these reactions the hydrogen is accepted by NAD+ and in one reaction it is accepted by FAD.<br>
The energy released by the oxidation reactions is stored in the electron carriers and used to make ATP at a later point.<br><br>One molecule of ATP is produced directly in one of these reactions. <a data-href="Phosphorylation" href="\definitions\phosphorylation.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Phosphorylation</a> occurs, however not powered by an enzyme, rather powered directly by an bond breaking.<br><br><img alt="Cellular Respiration ETC Diagram.png" src="\lib\media\cellular-respiration-etc-diagram.png"><br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Oxidation and Reduction Reactions" data-href="Oxidation and Reduction Reactions" href="\definitions\oxidation-and-reduction-reactions.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Reduced</a> <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Electron Carriers" data-href="Electron Carriers" href="\definitions\electron-carriers.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">NAD</a> and FADH2 donate their electrons to electron carriers found in the inner membrane of the mitochondria. As the electrons are passed from carrier to carrier energy is utilized by proton pumps to transfer protons across the inner membrane from the matrix and into the inter-membrane space. The protons then flow through <a data-href="ATP Synthase" href="\definitions\atp-synthase.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">ATP Synthase</a> down their concentration gradient providing the energy needed to make ATP.<br><br> Oxygen is needed to bind with the free protons exiting the electron transport chain to maintain the hydrogen gradient, resulting in the formation of water]]></description><link>unit-3\cellular-respiration.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 3/Cellular Respiration.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 07:37:12 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\labeled-mitochondria-structural-diagram.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\labeled-mitochondria-structural-diagram.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Carbon Fixation]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>The light-independent stage does not require sunlight and thus takes place at all times, given there is enough ATP.<br><br>The process of converting inorganic carbon (CO2) to organic compounds (Glucose, C6H12O6). This takes place during photosynthesis in the fluid, or the stroma of <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Chloroplasts" data-href="Chloroplasts" href="\definitions\chloroplasts.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">chloroplasts</a>. This is a cyclical process, called the Calvin Cycle. 6 turns of the cycle are required to produce one molecule of glucose.<br><br><img alt="Stages of the Calvin Cycle.png" src="\lib\media\stages-of-the-calvin-cycle.png" style="width: 600px; max-width: 100%;"><br>The carbon from a molecule of CO2, marked as 1C at the top left of the cycle, goes through the process to exit at the bottom left of the cycle as a free, organic carbon molecule. (Process described below.)<br>Underlined things you need to memorize, the rest you need to understand.<br><br>Carbon dioxide (1C) combines with the 5C sugar Ribulose bisphosphate (RuBP) to give two 3C molecules, glycerate 3 phosphate (GP).<br><br>Carbon dioxide (1C) + Ribulose bisphosphate (5C) = 2 x Glycerate 3 phosphate (3C)<br>CO2 + RuBP = 2GP<br>This reaction is catalyzed by the enzyme ribulose bisphosphate carboxylase (rubisco), which is the most common enzyme found in green plants.<br><br>GP, in the presence of ATP and NADPH, is reduced (loses electrons) to TP (a less stable molecule.) <br><br>2xGlycerate 3 phosphate (3C) + ATP/NADPH = 2xTriose phosphate (3C) (+ADP/NADP)<br>2GP + ATP/NADPH = 2TP<br><br>From the two TP molecules (6C), one carbon is released to form glucose. The other five carbons are needed to produce Ribulose biphosphate.<br>The remaining two TP molecules (one no longer a tp molecule as it has lost a carbon), join together to form RuBP, converting 3 ATP to ADP.<br>Glucose has 6 carbons, thus 6 instances of the cycle must complete to for a glucose molecule.<br><br>]]></description><link>unit-3\light-independent-stage.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 3/Light-Independent Stage.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Feb 2024 05:52:22 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\stages-of-the-calvin-cycle.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\stages-of-the-calvin-cycle.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Function of Photosynthesis]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Photosynthesis is a process conducted in <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Chloroplasts" data-href="Chloroplasts" href="\definitions\chloroplasts.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">chloroplasts</a>, converting CO2 and H2O and producing C6H12O6 (Sugars) and O2.<br><img alt="Photosynthesis Equation.jpg" src="\lib\media\photosynthesis-equation.jpg" style="width: 500px; max-width: 100%;"><br><br>Photosynthesis can be broken down into two stages, the first being the light-dependent stage(LDS), which, as implied by the name can only take place when light is present. The products of the Light Dependent Reaction are ATP, NADPH and H+.<br><img alt="Light-Dependent Stage Diagram.png" src="\lib\media\light-dependent-stage-diagram.png" style="width: 600px; max-width: 100%;"><br><br><img alt="Photosystem Diagram.png" src="\lib\media\photosystem-diagram.png" style="width: 300px; max-width: 100%;"><br>The LDS begins in photosystem 2. (Despite the name, which refers to it being discovered after photosystem 1) <br><a data-href="Photosynthetic Pigments" href="\definitions\photosynthetic-pigments.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Photosynthetic Pigments</a>, labeled on the diagram above as "Pigment molecules" get excited by photons of sunlight, to the point of losing electrons that are then lost, hopping between pigment molecules, to the "reaction-center complex" which is a specific molecule of Chlorophyl a. The reaction-center complex enters a high-energy state, said to be "photoactivated", and as a result, high energy electrons are released.<br><br>The holes left behind by the lost excited electrons are positively charged and are powerful enough to split water molecules into hydrogen and oxygen. This is called photolysis.<br>The process of photolysis uses enzymes that are found in Photosystem II, as a result, hydrogen ions, electrons (unexcited) and oxygen atoms are released. Additionally, the holes are refilled with electrons.<br>H2O 2H++ 2e- +  ½O2<br>The oxygen atoms combine and are released as a waste product.<br><br>The high energy electrons released from Photosystem II are passed along a chain of electron carriers. This provides the energy needed to pump hydrogen ions from the stroma into the thylakoid space. Said transfer of excited electrons occurs between carriers in the thylakoid membranes<br><br>The use of light energy to convert ADP to ATP. Conducted by <a data-href="ATP Synthase" href="\definitions\atp-synthase.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">ATP Synthase</a> across the membrane of the thylakoid space. <br><a data-href="Phosphorylation" href="\definitions\phosphorylation.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Phosphorylation</a><br><br>The high energy electrons lost from PS2, which lost their energy to the proton pumps, arrive at Photosystem I and fill the holes in the reaction center created by the photoactivation of the primary pigment. Photoactivation of Photosystem I also creates ‘excited’ electrons. These combine with the hydrogen ions from photolysis to reduce NADP+<br>2H+  +  2e-  +  NADP 	<br>Excited electrons from Photosystem I are used to reduce NADP.<br><br>
<br>Light Strength and Color
<br>Chlorophyl
<br>Water
<br>Substrate concentration (CO2)
<br>]]></description><link>unit-3\photosynthesis.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 3/Photosynthesis.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Feb 2024 14:41:59 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\photosynthesis-equation.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\photosynthesis-equation.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[1. <a data-href="Photosynthesis" href="unit-3/photosynthesis.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Photosynthesis</a>]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><br>The structure of the chloroplast is adapted to its function in photosynthesis.<br>Light dependent reactions take place in the intermembrane space of the thylakoids.<br>Absorption of light by photosystems generates excited electrons.<br>Photolysis of water generates electrons for use in the light-dependent reactions.<br>Transfer of excited electrons occurs between carriers in the thylakoid membranes.<br>Excited electrons from Photosystem I are used to reduce NADP.<br>Light-independent reactions take place in the stroma.<br>(All the equations involved in the light independent and dependent reactions.)<br>In the light-independent reactions a carboxylase enzyme catalyzes the carboxylation of ribulose biphosphate.<br>Glycerate 3-phosphate is reduced to triose phosphate using reduced NADP and ATP.<br>Triose phosphate is used to regenerate RuBP and produce carbohydrates.<br>Ribulose biphosphate is reformed using ATP.<br><br><br>Cell respiration involves the oxidation and reduction of electron carriers<br>In glycolysis, glucose is converted to pyruvate in the cytoplasm.<br>Phosphorylation of molecules makes them less stable<br>Glycolysis gives a small net gain of ATP without the use of oxygen<br>In aerobic respiration pyruvate is decarboxylated and oxidized, and converted into acetyl compound. In the link reaction this is attached to coenzyme A to form acetyl coenzyme A.<br>In the Krebs cycle, the oxidation of acetyl groups is coupled to the reduction of hydrogen carriers, liberating carbon dioxide.<br>Energy released by oxidation reactions is carried to the cristae of the mitochondria by reduced NAD and FAD.<br>Transfer of electrons between carriers in the electron transport chain in the membrane of the cristae is coupled to proton pumping.<br>In chemiosmosis protons diffuse through ATP synthase to generate ATP.<br>Oxygen is needed to bind with the free protons to maintain the hydrogen gradient, resulting in the formation of water.<br>The structure of the mitochondrion is adapted to the function it performs.<br><br><a data-href="Decarboxylation" href="\definitions\decarboxylation.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Decarboxylation</a><br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Cellular Respiration > 2. The Link Reaction" data-href="Cellular Respiration#2. The Link Reaction" href="\unit-3\cellular-respiration.html#2._The_Link_Reaction" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Oxidative Decarboxylation</a><br>
<a data-href="ATP Synthase" href="\definitions\atp-synthase.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">ATP Synthase</a><br><br>Annotation of a diagram of a mitochondrion to indicate the adaptations to its function.<br>
(<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Labeled Mitochondria Structural Diagram.png" data-href="Labeled Mitochondria Structural Diagram.png" href="\files-and-refferences\labeled-mitochondria-structural-diagram.png" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Annotated Diagram</a>)  CORRECTION : INTERMEMBRANE SPACE "PROTONS ARE PUMPED"<br><img alt="Mitochondria Microscope Image.png" src="\lib\media\mitochondria-microscope-image.png" style="width: 300px; max-width: 100%;"><br>]]></description><link>unit-3\unit-3-study-order.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 3/Unit 3 - Study Order.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 18 Feb 2024 07:27:46 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\mitochondria-microscope-image.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\mitochondria-microscope-image.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Genetic Material In Humans]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>There are 42 chromosomes in humans. Humans have 46,000 genes. There are approximately 25,000 genes which are transcribed into mRNA in order to make proteins, and additional sequences that produce other forms of RNA (tRNA and rRNA) other than mRNA. The remaining genes were nicknames 'Junk' DNA.<br><br>Telomeres are sort of "caps" on the ends of DNA, which protect the DNA when cloned. <br><img alt="Pasted image 20240219144701.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240219144701.png"><br>With each cloning of a chromosome, the telomeres shortens, until eventually the DNA itself decays, inhibiting cell replication. In younger people telomerase replaces the telomere, but this process decreases with age, due to the availability of telomerase. Telomeres are shortened as we age, but telomeres can also be shortened by stress, smoking, obesity, lack of exercise and a&nbsp;poor diet.<br><br>In eukaryotes the immediate product of mRNA transcription is pre-mRNA. The pre-mRNA must be modified to become mature mRNA. Modification is done using splicing. <br>Splicing removes any junk DNA that has been transcribed. The junk DNA that is removed is called intervening sequences or INTRONS. <br>These introns must be removed. The remaining sequences of DNA that will code for proteins are called EXONS. <br>Introns are removed and the remaining exons are spliced together to form the mature mRNA. <br>Different orders of splicing introns together can form coding for different proteins.<br><img alt="Pasted image 20240519231154.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240519231154.png">]]></description><link>unit-4\&apos;junk&apos;-dna-and-telomeres.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 4/&apos;Junk&apos; DNA and Telomeres.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2024 15:59:57 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\pasted-image-20240219144701.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\pasted-image-20240219144701.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Cancer]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Tumours can either be benign, which means they are restricted to that tissue or organ, or malignant (cancerous) where some of the abnormal cells migrate to other tissues or organs and continue to grow further tumours there.<br>Cancer occurs when cells from a primary tumour migrate to other tissues to form new secondary tumours in a process known as metastasis.<br><img alt="Pasted image 20240512211804.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240512211804.png" style="width: 650px; max-width: 100%;"><br><br>Cancer is caused by damage of genetic material.<br>DNA can be modified by physical, chemical and biological agents, known as mutagens. Mutagens can include:<br>
<br>Ionizing radiation such as X-rays, gamma rays and UV
<br>Chemical Compounds like those in tobacco smoke
<br>Aflatoxins produced by fungi.
<br>Mutagens that cause cancer are known as carcinogens.<br><br>Many tumors can be caused by mistakenly activating oncogenes. (Abnormal genes with the potential to cause cancer.)<br>Oncogenes are inheritable. The more oncogenes you have the higher likelihood of one of them being activated and causing cancer.]]></description><link>unit-4\cancer.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 4/Cancer.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 12 May 2024 16:19:58 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\pasted-image-20240512211804.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\pasted-image-20240512211804.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Cell Division]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>New cells arise by division of existing cells. In these processes, it is important that the two new cells produced by each division on a cell contain identical sets of chromosomes.<br><br><img alt="Pasted image 20240512190834.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240512190834.png" style="width: 500px; max-width: 100%;"><br><br>Always the longest part of the cell cycle, variable in length. <br>When growth is fast, (a developing embryo or at the growing point of a young stem cell), interphase may last 24 hours or less. <br>In mature cells that infrequently divide it can last longer. (Some cells, once differentiated may never divide again.)<br>During interphase there is intense biochemical activity in the nucleus and cytoplasm, proteins and new organelles are being synthesized, and before nuclear division there is an accumulation of stored energy.<br><br>Growth and normal metabolic processes. All cellular organelles except chromosomes duplicated.<br><br>DNA replication<br><br>Growth and preparation for mitosis / meiosis. The cell repairs any errors in duplicated chromosomes <br><br>After interphase, <a data-href="Meiosis" href="\unit-4\meiosis.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Meiosis</a> or <a data-href="Mitosis" href="\unit-4\mitosis.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Mitosis</a> takes place.<br><br>During cell division cellular organelles become even distributed between cells. <br>In animal cells a fibrous ring composed of a protein called actin forms around the center of the cell and contracts pinching the cytoplasm in half.<br>In plant cells the Golgi apparatus forms vesicles containing new cell wall materials, which collect along the line of the equator of the spindle, this is known as the cell plate. Here the vesicles join forming the new plasma membranes and cell walls between the two cells.<br><img alt="Pasted image 20240512193841.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240512193841.png"><br><br>A family of proteins that control the progression of cells through the cell cycle by activating cyclin-dependent kinase enzymes (CDKs). <br>These enzymes control specific events such as microtubule formation and chromatid alignment.<br>Cyclins can be divided into four types based on their different behavior:<br><img alt="Pasted image 20240512194029.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240512194029.png"><br><br>S cyclins induce DNA replication. Their levels remain high throughout S phase, G2 and the first part of mitosis to promote early events in mitosis.<br><br>M cyclin influence the formation of mitotic spindles and alignment of sister chromatids along them.<br><br>G1 cyclin levels gradually rise and fall throughout the cell cycle, influenced by cell growth. G1 cyclins coordinate cell growth and the start of a new cell cycle.<br><br>G1/ S cyclins start the initial process of DNA replication.]]></description><link>unit-4\cell-division-+-cell-cycle-+-cytokenisis.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 4/Cell Division + Cell Cycle + Cytokenisis.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2024 15:59:31 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\pasted-image-20240512190834.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\pasted-image-20240512190834.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[DNA Replication]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><img alt="Simple DNA Replication Diagram.png" src="\lib\media\simple-dna-replication-diagram.png" style="width: 700px; max-width: 100%;"><br>
DNA Replication is a semi-conservative process, meaning that one original strand of DNA is incorporated into two new strands.<br><img alt="Labeled DNA Replication Diagram.png" src="\lib\media\labeled-dna-replication-diagram.png" style="width: 700px; max-width: 100%;"><br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TNKWgcFPHqw" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TNKWgcFPHqw" target="_blank">DNA replication - 3D (youtube.com)</a><br><br><img alt="DNA Replication Processes.png" src="\lib\media\dna-replication-processes.png" style="width: 700px; max-width: 100%;"><br><br>Replication begins at a site called the "Origin of replication", where DNA helicase unwinds the DNA. This process is called a "Replication fork" <br><br>As the DNA is unwound, specific single stranded DNA binding proteins prevent the strands from reannealing.<br>
Here, DNA Gyrase relieves the torque formed by unwinding DNA. <br><br>Short sequences of RNA, called primers, are produced by the enzyme primase and bind to the DNA. <br><br>Then DNA polymerase III binds and begins to synthesize the DNA complementary bases to the parental strand.<br>
DNA polymerase III lowers the activation energy necessary for the complementary bases to attach.<br>
The bases are on nucleoside triphosphate molecules, which lose two of the phosphates, converting to nucleotides, much like ATP, providing the energy needed to form the bonds.<br>
Hydrogen bonds are formed between the nucleoside triphosphate and its complementary base on the exposed DNA strand. <br><br>Once the complementary strand is formed, the enzyme DNA polymerase I removes the RNA primers and replaces them with DNA.<br>
DNA Polymerase I can only add nucleotides at the 3' end.<br>
The RNA primers being removed leaves gaps. <br><br>Ligase essentially glues together the remaining gaps with nucleotides.<br><br>DNA polymerase can only add nucleotides to the 3' end of a primer, thus the two new strands of DNA are built slightly differently. <br>Continuous replication occurs on the Leading Strand. Discontinuous replication occurs on the Lagging Strand.<br>The fragments that are made on the lagging strand are called Okazaki fragments.]]></description><link>unit-4\dna-replication.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 4/DNA Replication.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2024 08:51:10 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\simple-dna-replication-diagram.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\simple-dna-replication-diagram.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[DNA Structure]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><img alt="Pasted image 20240305120541.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240305120541.png" style="width: 300px; max-width: 100%;"><br>DNA&nbsp;winds into a double helix, with hydrogen bonding between the bases of each strand like the rungs of a ladder. <br>This&nbsp;structure&nbsp;enables&nbsp;DNA&nbsp;to coil so that the long molecule is compact and lots of information can be stored in a small space.<br><br>A nucleosome is a core group of eight histone proteins arranged to form an Octomer, held together by an additional histone protein that attaches to the DNA molecule. <br>Only eukaryotic DNA has nucleosomes.<br>DNA is repeatedly wrapped around the nucleosome which allows supercoiling, which in turn allows a huge molecule to occupy a relatively small space (inside the nucleus). <br><img alt="Pasted image 20240305120725.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240305120725.png" style="width: 500px; max-width: 100%;"><br>Nucleosomes are then linked together to form what is called a solenoid fiber. This is the supercoiled structure of chromatin.<br><br>There are two types of bases: Purines and Pyrimidines<br>Adenine and Guanine are larger, purine bases.<br>
Thymine and Cytosine are smaller, pyrimidine bases.  <br>A purine always pairs with a pyrimidine<br>Adenine always pairs with Thymine (with two hydrogen bonds.)<br>
Guanine always pairs with Cytosine (with three hydrogen bonds.)<br>AT GC]]></description><link>unit-4\dna-structure.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 4/DNA Structure.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 10:04:27 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\pasted-image-20240305120541.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\pasted-image-20240305120541.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR)]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>A technique to duplicate the DNA from a sample. Useful for producing a larger sample for analysis. DNA from very small samples of semen, blood, or even fossils can be amplified using PCR.<br>Stages of PCR:<br>
<br>Denaturing of the DNA using high temperatures, to separate the two strands into smaller fragments.
<br>DNA polymerase form a bacterium thermophilus aquaticus, which can withstand these temperatures, is added.
<br>Free nucleotides are paired and new strands are produced.
<br><br><img alt="Pasted image 20240501111321.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240501111321.png"><br>This is a method of separating mixtures of proteins, DNA or other molecules that carry a charge. <br>The mixture is placed inside sheet of jell, which acts like a resistance, much like a molecular sieve. Depending on the strength and polarity of the charge, as well as the size of molecules, with the charge applied to the jell, they get pulled away from the origin points different amounts. This produces a pattern on the jell.<br>These patterns are very unlikely to be the same for any two individuals.<br>
Analysis of the bands of DNA is a technique called DNA profiling.<br><img alt="Pasted image 20240501111940.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240501111940.png"><br><br>Humans and other organisms have short sequences of bases that are repeated many times called satellite DNA. (Junk DNA) <br>This satellite DNA varies greatly between individuals in the number of repeats. <br>If the DNA is copied using PCR and then cut up into short fragments using restriction enzymes, the lengths of the fragments varies greatly between individuals. <br>Such variations exist throughout the genome and can be used to define a unique genetic fingerprint.]]></description><link>unit-4\genetic-engineering-and-biotechnology.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 4/Genetic Engineering and Biotechnology.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2024 06:25:31 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\pasted-image-20240501111321.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\pasted-image-20240501111321.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Genetic Modification of Bacteria to Produce Human Insulin]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><img alt="Pasted image 20240508110346.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240508110346.png">]]></description><link>unit-4\genetic-modification-of-bacteria-to-produce-human-insulin.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 4/Genetic Modification of Bacteria to Produce Human Insulin.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2024 06:03:47 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\pasted-image-20240508110346.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\pasted-image-20240508110346.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Karyotypes and Karyotyping]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Mapping out the number of chromosomes in an organism.<br>Human male karyotype:<br>
<img alt="Pasted image 20240512201958.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240512201958.png" style="width: 300px; max-width: 100%;"><br>There are two procedures for obtaining foetal chromosomes to produce the karyotype:<br>
<br>Amniocentesis<br>
A needle is passed through the abdominal and uterus walls of the mother, using ultrasound to guide the needle. The needle is used to withdraw a sample of the amniotic fluid from the amniotic sac of the developing foetus. Cells from the foetus that can be found in the amniotic fluid are cultured and then used to prepare a karyotype.
<br>Chorionic villus sampling (CVS)<br>
Cells are removed from the chorionic villi tissue in the placenta. It is possible to insert the sampling tool through the vagina.
]]></description><link>unit-4\karyotypes-and-karyotyping.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 4/Karyotypes and Karyotyping.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 12 May 2024 15:25:56 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\pasted-image-20240512201958.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\pasted-image-20240512201958.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Law of Independent Assortment]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>9:3:3:1 ratio if two parents, heterozygous for two traits reproduce. (Dihybrid crosses)<br>16 possible offspring. <br><img alt="Pasted image 20240606093910.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240606093910.png" style="width: 500px; max-width: 100%;">]]></description><link>unit-4\law-of-independent-assortment.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 4/Law of Independent Assortment.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 06 Jun 2024 04:40:12 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\pasted-image-20240606093910.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\pasted-image-20240606093910.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Meiosis]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Making sex cells (gametes). Half of the chromosomes in a cell are duplicated to form a cell with a half the genetic information / chromosomes. <br>Meiosis is a reduction division of a diploid nucleus (2n) to form haploid nuclei (n).<br><img alt="Pasted image 20240409120936.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240409120936.png" style="width: 500px; max-width: 100%;"><br><br><br>The cell has two full sets of chromosomes. (Two of each type of chromosome (one maternal and one paternal)). <br>Each pair of chromosomes have the same genes, arranged in the same sequence. However, they do not usually have the same alleles of all of these genes. They are therefore not identical but instead are homologous.<br>Homologous chromosomes form pairs within the nucleus and during cell division. The pair shares certain structural characteristics:<br>
• they are the same length<br>
• they have the same shape<br>
• they carry the same genes in the same gene loci<br><img alt="Pasted image 20240512201958.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240512201958.png" style="width: 300px; max-width: 100%;"><br><br>The cell contains only one of each chromosomes and therefore has just one set.<br><br>Meiosis is defined by the halving of the number of chromosomes:<br>
1. During interphase, the chromosomes replicate. Each chromosome consists of two identical chromatids.<br>
2. At the start of meiosis I, homologous chromosomes pair up. The homologous chromosomes exchange genetic material with each other in a process called crossing over.<br>
3. During meiosis II, the homologous pairs of chromosomes separate. One of each pair goes to each of the two daughter cells. The result is two diploid daughter cells.<br>
4. In meiosis II, the two daughter nuclei divide again. This time the chromatids of each chromosome separate. Meiosis II is similar to mitosis. The end result is four haploid cells that are genetically different.<br><br>Meiosis is sometimes subject to errors, for example when homologous chromosomes fail to separate at anaphase. This is called non-disjunction. <br>The result will be a gamete that either has an extra chromosome or is deficient in a chromosome. If the gamete is involved in human fertilization, the offspring will either have 45 or 47 chromosomes.<br>For example Trisomy 21, also known as Down’s syndrome is due to non-disjunction that leaves the individual with three of chromosome 21 instead of two. <br>Features of the syndrome include hearing loss, heart and vision disorders, mental and growth retardation.  ]]></description><link>unit-4\meiosis.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 4/Meiosis.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2024 16:11:43 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\pasted-image-20240409120936.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\pasted-image-20240409120936.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Mitosis]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>The division of a eukaryotic nucleus into two genetically identical daughter nuclei<br>The 4 phases described below aren't concrete, definitions will vary.<br>Before mitosis can occur, two copies of each chromosome are needed. <br>Each chromosome initially consists of a single DNA molecule called chromatin. During interphase DNA is replicated so that it then consists of two identical DNA molecules, these are called sister chromatids. <br><img alt="Pasted image 20240512191918.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240512191918.png" style="width: 600px; max-width: 100%;"><br><br>Chromosomes become visible as chromatin shorten and thicken through supercoiling.<br>Sister chromatins are held together by the centromere.<br>The chromatin increasingly shortens and thickens by a process of supercoiling until the . Only at the end of prophase is it possible to see that they actually consist of two sister chromatids held together at the centromere.<br>At the same time the nucleolus gradually disappears and the nuclear membrane breaks down.<br><br>The centrosomes / centrioles move to opposite ends of the cell. Microtubules in the cytoplasm start to form into a spindle, radiating out from the centrosomes. Microtubules attach to the kinetochores of each pair of chromatids, which then migrate to the equator of the spindle. <br><img alt="Pasted image 20240512193546.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240512193546.png" style="width: 300px; max-width: 100%;"><br><br>The spindle microtubules contract, the centromeres divide and the chromatids are pulled to opposite poles of the cell.<br>Once separated the chromatids are referred to once more as chromosomes.<br><br>The nuclear membrane reforms around both groups of chromosomes at opposite ends of the cell. The chromosomes uncoil becoming chromatin again. The nucleolus reforms in each nucleus.]]></description><link>unit-4\mitosis.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 4/Mitosis.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2024 16:10:39 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\pasted-image-20240512191918.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\pasted-image-20240512191918.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Mitotic Index]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>The ratio of the number of cells undergoing mitosis per total cells is called the mitotic index.<br>The index is used as a prognostic tool, a low mitotic index in a tumor suggests the treatment is working.]]></description><link>unit-4\the-mitotic-index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 4/The Mitotic Index.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 12 May 2024 16:21:51 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Transcription]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><br>RNA polymerase binds to a promoter region (a non-coding DNA with the sole purpose of marking a spot on the DNA), which is the start signal for transcription, located immediately before the gene.<br><br>mRNA has a base sequence complementary to the DNA template strand and identical to the other strand (with the exception of uracil replacing thymine). <br>The DNA strand with the same base sequence as the mRNA is called the sense strand. The other strand, the one that acts as a template, is called the anti-sense strand.<br><br>In eukaryotes, each cell has a set of DNA coding for the organism as a whole. Only a part of this is expressed in each cell.<br>For example, a gene for the production of insulin is present in all cells of the body but it is only active in the cells in the pancreas. <br>This can be influenced by the environment. For example, if blood sugar levels are low then insulin will not be produced. <br>There are several mechanisms for controlling which genes are expressed.<br><br>Gene regulation is when a physical barrier is made such that specific segments of DNA can not be read by enzymes. There are 2 ways this can be achieved.<br><br>Nucleosomes, by bunching up DNA, can help regulate transcription because they make certain parts of the DNA inaccessible.<br><img alt="Pasted image 20240221110052.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240221110052.png" style="width: 700px; max-width: 100%;"><br><br>Regulatory proteins can bond to regulatory elements on DNA, to limit sections from being read.<br><img alt="Pasted image 20240519230938.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240519230938.png" style="width: 700px; max-width: 100%;">]]></description><link>unit-4\transcription-and-gene-expression.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 4/Transcription and gene expression.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2024 16:01:46 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\pasted-image-20240221110052.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\pasted-image-20240221110052.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Learning Statements]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>
<br>A gene is a heritable factor that controls a specific characteristic. 
<br>A genome is the whole of the genetic information of an organism.
<br>An allele is one specific form of a gene, differing from other alleles by one or a few bases only and occupying the same gene locus as other alleles of the same gene.
<br>Gene mutation is a change to the base sequence of a gene.
<br>Meiosis is a reduction division of a diploid nucleus (2n) to form haploid nuclei (n)
<br>Homologous chromosomes have the same genes as each other, in the same sequence, but not necessarily the same allele of those genes.
<br>The process of Meiosis
<br>Th
]]></description><link>unit-4\unit-5-guide.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 4/Unit 5 Guide.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 19 May 2024 18:22:18 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Animal Classification Activity]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><img alt="Pasted image 20240916143809.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240916143809.png"><br>
<br>Does it have feathers? Yes, chicken, no Q2
<br>Does it have an elongated neck? Yes, gerenuk, no Q3
<br>Does it have elongated ears? Yes, rabbit, no Q4
<br>Does it have a beak? Yes, kiwi, no Tahr
]]></description><link>unit-5\animal-classification-activity.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 5/Animal Classification Activity.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 09:41:49 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\pasted-image-20240916143809.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\pasted-image-20240916143809.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Antibiotic Resistance]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Evolution is demonstrated in the development of antibiotic resistance in bacteria.<br>The development of Antibiotic Resistance:<br>
<br>Bacteria multiply, some more resistant to antibiotics than others,
<br>Antibiotics are introduced, representing an environmental pressure and start killing off the population, starting with the weakest.
<br>People tend to stop taking antibiotics when symptoms fade, as opposed to taking them as long as they are supposed to, leaving the most resistant bacteria alive.
<br>The most resistant bacteria multiply, now the whole population more resistant to antibiotics.
]]></description><link>unit-5\antibiotic-resistance.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 5/Antibiotic Resistance.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 08:30:28 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Formatting]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Classification is the human labeling of speciation and species. Allows for international communication through a standard. Created by Carl Linnaeus, as he used it in his book "Species Plantarum". Discussed in the first International Zoological Congress in Paris 1889.<br><br>Genus species - Genus first letter in capital, other is small. In italics.<br>Hierarch of Taxonomy (The ranking of groups) <br>
<br>Domain,
<br>Kingdom,
<br>Phylum,
<br>Class
<br>Order
<br>Family
<br>Genus
<br>Species
<br>(Dear king paddy can only fight going sideways.)<br><br><br>A new addition to the taxonomy;<br>
<br>Archaea,
<br>Bacteria,
<br>Eukaryotes
<br>Viruses do not classify into any domain.<br><br>
<br>Prokaryotes,
<br>Animalia,
<br>Plantae,
<br>Protoctista,
<br>Fungi,
<br><br>Grouping species according to common (shared) traits. I.E. Mammals make milk for their young.<br>Today, DNA analysis is used.<br>The smaller the group, the more similar the members.]]></description><link>unit-5\biological-classification.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 5/Biological Classification.md</guid><pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 08:58:48 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Clades]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>A group of organisms with a common ancestor. Can be determined from base sequence of a gene, or amino acid sequence in proteins.<br>Extinct : Living.<br>
Extant : Not yet extinct.<br><br>Sequence differences happen fairly regularly over time, so we as differences can be mapped, as segments of time, so we can know how long ago a divergence happened.<br><br>Tree diagrams that show the most probable sequence of divergence in clades.<br><img alt="Pasted image 20240919133419.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240919133419.png" style="width: 700px; max-width: 100%;">]]></description><link>unit-5\cladistics.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 5/Cladistics.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2024 08:44:05 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\pasted-image-20240919133419.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\pasted-image-20240919133419.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Evolution]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Evolution occurs when heritable characteristics of a species change. Evolution only concerns heritable characteristics. (Most traits are a combination of heritable and acquired.)<br><br>Populations of a species can gradually diverge into separate species by evolution. Once they can no longer reproduce and produce fertile offspring, they are different species.<br>Speciation occurs when a population of a species is isolated from the larger group. I.E. birds migrate to another island / river forms between a population.<br><br><br>The fossil record creates chronological evidence of evolution, seen in changed bone structure.<br>
<br>The complexity makes sense over time. (algae then fungi then land vertebrates etc.)
<br>Fits with ecology, plant fossils appeared before animal fossils, plants on land before animals on land.
<br>Many sequences of fossils are known which link together existing organisms with their likely ancestors.
<br><br>Selective breeding was able to manually control evolution. Wild Jungle fowl were bred into egg-laying hens. Dogs were bred for human use, domesticated over only 1500 years.<br><br>
<br>Convergent; From different sources, two species can evolve to similar structures to match a similar environment, however may be no related at all. I.E (butterflies and hummingbirds)
<br>Divergent; From the same source, two vastly different species can evolve. One similar element can prove they are connected, for example the Pentadactyl Limb.
<br><img alt="Pasted image 20240814140856.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20240814140856.png" style="width: 450px; max-width: 100%;"><br><br>
<br>Isolated populations of species optimized for different environments over time. (I.E. finch beaks match food source.)
<br>Patterns / similarities between species point to ancestor.
<br>The process for industrial melanism:<br>
i. Adult Biston betularia moths fly at night to reproduce<br>
ii. During the day they roost on trees<br>
iii. Birds and other animals hunt moths during the day<br>
iv. In polluted areas soot blackens trees<br>
v. Melanic moths are well camouflaged against dark trees in polluted areas<br>
vi. In polluted areas the melanic variety of Biston betularia replaced the pale peppered moth variety over a relatively short time, but not in non-polluted areas<br><br>Species that clone themselves can not evolve. There is no variation.]]></description><link>unit-5\evolution.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 5/Evolution.md</guid><pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2024 16:50:42 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\pasted-image-20240814140856.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\pasted-image-20240814140856.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Variation]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Survival of the fittest. Some individuals in a population are better suited for the environment than others.<br>
<br>Species tend to produce more offspring than the environment can support.
<br>This can lead to a struggle for existence.
<br>There is variation between individuals in a species.
<br>Some individuals are better adapted to the environment than others
<br>Individuals that are better adapted are more likely to survive and produce offspring.
<br>Individuals that reproduce pass on such favorable characteristics to their offspring.
<br>This leads to an increase in favorable characteristics and therefore changes within the species.
<br><br>There are 3 main sources of variation;<br>
<br>Mutation.
<br>Crossing over. The combination of 2 gametes, resulting in a new unique sequence of DNA
<br>The process leading up to the gametes combine. ( Which organisms mate and which sperm / egg fuse. )
<br><br>Characteristics which allow organisms that live in their environment. Develops through generations, not lifetimes.]]></description><link>unit-5\natural-selection.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 5/Natural Selection.md</guid><pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2024 05:46:27 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Theoretical (Mendelian) Genetics]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Through observing peas, Gregor Mendel identified there was a unit of inheritance, noting the presence of dominant and recessive genes.]]></description><link>unit-5\theoretical-(mendelian)-genetics.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 5/Theoretical (Mendelian) Genetics.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2024 06:23:05 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Carbon Fixation]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Moving gaseous carbon in to a solid form, I.E, organic molecules in plants.<br>Autotrophs (photosynthetic organisms) carbon fixate.<br><br>Biosphere, Atmosphere, Geosphere, Hydrosphere. (Reservoirs/pools of carbon dioxide.)<br>These 'spheres' have the ability to contain CO2 in a variety of forms. <br><br>Photosynthesis by terrestrial plants and algae (freshwater and oceans) in which atmospheric (and dissolved) carbon dioxide is removed and fixed as organic compounds such as carbohydrate, lipid and protein<br>Respiration by all organisms in which they metabolise organic molecules releasing carbon dioxide<br>Feeding, in which the carbon of organic molecules is move from one link in the food chain to another<br>Fossilization in which carbon as organic molecules becomes trapped in sediment as coal, gas and oil<br>Combustion during the burning of fossil fuels and burning of biomass<br><br>Bacteria that produce methane. (Methanogenesis)<br>
In the atmosphere, methane is oxidized into CO2 and Water.<br><br>Peat is the stuff that would become coal or oil, if there was enough compression over enough time. A layer of rotting dead organic material, with lots of bacteria.<br>Peat forms when soils is waterlogged, or dues to other factors, bacteria can not live in it and decompose it.<br><br>Partially decomposed organic matter from past geological eras was converted either into coal or into oil and gas that accumulate in porous rocks. (Through the effects of heat and pressure on peats.)<br>Carbon dioxide is produced by the combustion of biomass and fossilized organic matter.<br><br>Limestone is a part of the geosphere, usually underwater though.<br>Animals such as reef-building corals and Mollusca have hard parts that are composed of calcium carbonate and can become fossilized in limestone.<br>Approximately 10% of all sedimentary rock on Earth is limestone. About 12% of the mass of calcium carbonate is carbon, so huge amounts of the carbon are locked up in limestone rock.<br><br>Respiration and Photosynthesis is in our best estimations balanced, but our impact on nature is offsetting that balance, increasing CO2 emissions.]]></description><link>unit-6\carbon-in-ecosystems.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 6/Carbon in Ecosystems.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 17:52:19 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Climate Change]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Concentrations of gasses present in the atmosphere, impact the climate below. <br>Certain "Greenhouse" gasses, reflect some wavelengths of light, trapping it below the atmosphere. In total they make up less than 1% of the atmosphere.<br>Water vapor retains heat as it condenses, therefore it radiates heat back to earth.<br>Global warming is good, and would occur without human intervention. Recently however it is excessive, due to human activity.<br><br><br>The sun emits short-wave radiation. Short wave radiation can penetrate the atmosphere, thus is stronger. Some is absorbed by the ozone layer.<br><br>Once short-wave radiation is reflected, it is converted to long-wave. Long-wave radiation is weaker, thus it can not penetrate the atmosphere.]]></description><link>unit-6\climate-change.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 6/Climate Change.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 17:52:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Energy Flow]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Ecosystems require a consistent inflow of energy, to maintain balance against losses in heat.<br>For most biological communities, this source is sunlight through photosynthesis. An example against this is chemotrophs in Vulcanic vents in the oceans.<br>Organisms can convert energy:<br>
<br>From light to chemical. (Photosynthesis)
<br>From Chemical to Kinetic. (Muscle contractions)
<br>From Chemical to Heat. (In fat cells)
<br>From Chemical to Electric. (in nerve cells)
<br> Heat is a metabolic byproduct. Living organisms cannot recapture heat from the environment, yet we need it to maintain enzyme function.<br>Only approximately 10% of energy flows from one stage to the next in trophic levels. With each level, the amount of energy available decreases.<br><img alt="Energy Flow and Trophic Levels Diagram.png" src="\lib\media\energy-flow-and-trophic-levels-diagram.png" style="width: 300px; max-width: 100%;"> <img alt="Pasted image 20241015122341.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20241015122341.png" style="width: 350px; max-width: 100%;"><br>
note, in the second image above, heat is lost AND some parts of the carcasses are returned to decomposers. There are unrelated<br>Ecologists can measure how much energy is added per year by groups of organisms to their biomass. This can be calculated per square meter. (Kcal / Meters2/ Year)]]></description><link>unit-6\energy-flow.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 6/Energy Flow.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2024 07:26:31 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\energy-flow-and-trophic-levels-diagram.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\energy-flow-and-trophic-levels-diagram.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Secondary Sex Characteristics]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>There are 3 uses of secondary sex characteristics;<br>
<br>Ensure the mate is the same species and correct sex,
<br>Signal sexual maturity,
<br>Signal immunological health,
<br><br><br>A group of organisms of the same species, that lives in the same area at the same time.<br>Species will often congregate in a population.<br>Benefits;<br>
<br>Defense and offense, strength in numbers,
<br>Mate finding, abundance of mates in environment,
<br>Sharing of resources, one unit does better than others,
<br>Cons;<br>
<br>Competition for resources, needed for all entities,
<br>Conflict in competition for mates and resources.
<br>Ease of disease spread.
<br><br>Populations- of different species- living in the sample place at once, interacting with each other.<br>All species are dependent on relationships and interactions with others.<br>Interactions are complex and multileveled<br><br>Autotrophic (Self-feeding), are animals that can produce their own nutrients or carbon compounds from CO2 or other simple substances.<br>Heterotrophic (feeding-on-others), organisms that sustain nutrition from other organisms.<br>Mixotrophic, both.<br><br>
<br>Carnivore<br>
Feeds on living organic matter of animals.
<br>Herbivore<br>
Feeds on living organic matter of plants.
<br>Omnivore<br>
Feeds on living organic matter of plants and animals.
<br>Detritovores<br>
Feeds on remains (rotting organic matter).
<br>Saprotrophs<br>
Feeds on remains, but digests externally by expelling enzymes, then absorbing nutrients. (Mushrooms work like this.)
<br><br>Tropic levels;<br>
<br>Producer,
<br>Primary consumer, Herbivore
<br>Secondary consumer, Carnivore
<br>Tertiary consumer, Top carnivore.
]]></description><link>unit-6\species-and-communities.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 6/Species and Communities.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 17:51:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Habitats]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Biotic(living) and Abiotic(non-living) factors determine the ease of growth of a species in an ecosystem. Common factors are:<br><br>External temperature affect all animals, especially those that do not maintain constant internal body temperatures. Extremes of temperature require special adaptations, so some species can survive them.<br><br>Animals vary in the amount of water that they require. Some animals are aquatic and must have water to live in and at the other extreme some animals including desert rats are adapted to survive in an environment where they are unlikely ever to drink water.<br><br>All species of animals breed at some stage in their life cycle. Some animals require a specific site and can only exist in areas where those sites are available. For example, mosquitoes need stagnant water in which to lay their eggs.<br><br>Many animal species are adapted to feed on specific food types and only inhabit areas where this food source is available. For example, blue whales feed on krill and will only live in areas of the ocean where krill are abundant.<br><br>Some species of animals establish and defend territories, either for feeding or breeding. This tends to give the species an even rather than a clumped distribution. For example, tawny owls defend a single territory throughout the whole of their adult lives.<br><br><img alt="Pasted image 20241114105730.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20241114105730.png" style="width: 600px; max-width: 100%;"><br>
Sampling is usually random.<br><br><br>Random sampling of areas(quadrats) within the territory occupied by a species.<br>
<img alt="Pasted image 20241114105830.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20241114105830.png" style="width: 300px; max-width: 100%;"> <img alt="Pasted image 20241114110037.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20241114110037.png" style="width: 300px; max-width: 100%;"><br><br>A line sampled. Particularly useful when there is a gradient in an abiotic variable.<br><img alt="Pasted image 20241114110427.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20241114110427.png" style="width: 600px; max-width: 100%;"><br><br>Biomass is the total dry weight of organic matter of a group of organisms or an ecosystem. Obtaining this measurement is destructive, thus sample sizes are kept as small as possible.<br>Useful in tracking trophic levels.<br>Method for measuring biomass<br>
<br>Collect a sample of all living organisms in the ecosystem – random sampling should be used.
<br>The organisms should be sorted into trophic levels
<br>The organisms are dried, by being placed in an oven at 60-800 C
<br>The mass of the organisms in each trophic level is measured using an electronic balance
<br>Drying and measuring the mass may be repeated to check that samples were completely dry.
<br><br>
<br>Herbivory (consumption of plants)
<br>Predation (consumption of animals)
<br>Parasitism (living off host)
<br>Competition (between organisms for resources)
<br>Mutualism (mutually beneficial interactions between species.)
<br>It is hard to perfectly classify tropic levels due to multiple sources of nutrition from different categories.<br><br>All of the biotic and abiotic resources that the organism interacts with are components of its niche.<br>The niche includes:<br>
<br>Habitat – where the species lives in the ecosystem
<br>Nutrition – how the species obtains its food
<br>Relationships – the interactions with other species in the ecosystem
<br>The fundamental niche of a species is its potential mode of existence given the adaptations of the species.<br>The realized niche of a species is its actual mode of existence which results from competition from other species.<br>If two species have exactly the same niche, adaptation is not possible, and one of the two species will inevitably prove to be the superior competitor. This species will cause the disappearance of the other from the ecosystem.  <br>The principle that only one species can ever occupy a niche in an ecosystem is called the competitive exclusion principle.<br><br>Types of ecosystems. (basically)<br><img alt="Pasted image 20241114112627.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20241114112627.png" style="width: 400px; max-width: 100%;"><br>Examples of types of ecosystems;<br>
<br>Desert
<br>Grassland
<br>Shrubland
<br>Temperate deciduous forest<br>
(A forest that looses it's leaves in fall.)
<br>Tropical rainforest
<br>Tundra<br>
Icy cold place.
<br><br>The growth and development of an environment. Abiotic factors influence biotic factors, and vice versa, as an environment develops towards a "climax", a stable state.<br><br>
<br>The amount of organic matter in the soil increases as organic matter released by plants and other organisms accumulates
<br>The soil becomes deeper as organic matter helps to bind mineral matter together
<br>The soil structure improves as the organic matter content rises, increasing the amount of water that can be retained and the rate at which excess water drains through.
<br>Soil erosion is reduced by the binding action of the roots of larger plants
<br>The amounts of mineral recycling increases, as the soil can hold larger amounts and more minerals are held in the increasing biomass of the community
<br><br>Growth of an ecosystem in an environment where living organisms have not previously existed. <br><br>Regrowth in areas where an ecosystem was/is present, but is replaced by other ecosystems, because of a change in conditions.<br><br>Population diversity; Within an environment, the diversity of species.<br>
Environmental diversity; Globally, the diversity of biomes<br><br><br>
<br>Use a random sampling technique to search for organisms in the ecosystem
<br>Identify each of the organisms found
<br>Count the total number of individuals of each species
<br>Calculate the index (D)
<br><img alt="Pasted image 20241115090934.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20241115090934.png"><br>
High D = very stable and ancient site<br>
Low D = pollution or disturbed site<br><br>Bioindicators<br>Change in population density of indicator species (species that thrive in specific conditions, I.E. high/low oxygen concentration) can represent change in certain environmental conditions.  <br>Change can be predicted over time by looking at:<br>
1. Historical records,<br>
2. A response to a particular stimulus in a controlled environment,<br>
3. spatial impact e.g. using different distances from the source of sewage pollution in a river as pollution will eventually spread more over time<br>Indicator species can indicate a consistent environment too, hinting at primary or secondary succession.]]></description><link>unit-7\biodiversity.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 7/Biodiversity.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 07:22:02 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\pasted-image-20241114105730.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\pasted-image-20241114105730.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Conservation]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Conservation is the preservation, restoration and/or protection of the planet’s natural resources and ecosystems.<br><br>
<br>Economical,

<br>Commodities may come from nature,
<br>Crop plants may be enhanced or discovered.
<br>Ecotourism.


<br>Ethical,

<br>Species' right to life,
<br>Cultural important to people,
<br>Future generations' experience of our world.


<br>Ecological,

<br>Global warming impacts,
<br>Impacts on different environments 


<br>Aesthetically,

<br>Beauty, 
<br>Artistic inspiration, 
<br>Mental health.


]]></description><link>unit-7\conservation.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 7/Conservation.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 07:36:54 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Extinction of Species]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Species are declared extinct, after no evidence is seen of them for 50 years.]]></description><link>unit-7\extinction-of-species.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 7/Extinction of Species.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 07:17:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Alien Species Introduction]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Humans through globalization are moving species around the world at an alarming rate.<br>Alien species can cause species extinction and can be controlled by manipulating the environment by, for example, introducing a predator of the alien, to kill them off.<br><br>The process by which chemical substances become more concentrated at each trophic level. Chemicals stick to the predator, accumulating with each prey.<br><img alt="Pasted image 20241118150252.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20241118150252.png" style="width: 700px; max-width: 100%;"><br><br>Ozone, O3. There is a layer of it, about 0.01ppm concentration, 20-50km above the surface of the earth, above the layer of greenhouse gasses.<br>The ozone layer reduces the quantity of radiation reading reaching the earth.<br><img alt="Pasted image 20241119115107.png" src="\lib\media\pasted-image-20241119115107.png" style="width: 400px; max-width: 100%;"><br>Seasonal gaps in the ozone layer appear, this is normal. The gaps are getting larger and more frequent, that is not.<br>Chlorofluorocarbons (CFCs) are the main cause of ozone depletion, aerosols. When hit by UV, chlorine is released and destroys O3 molecules.<br><br>
<br>Increased mutation rates, by causing damage to DNA
<br>Cancers, especially of the skin
<br>Severe sunburn and cataracts of the eye
<br>Damages DNA -&gt; Reduced rate of photosynthesis in plants and algae that will then affect the food chain.
<br><br>Isolated populations are more likely to go extinct. (mining, agriculture, urbanization and forestry can lead to fragmentation)]]></description><link>unit-7\impact-of-humans-on-ecosystems.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Unit 7/Impact of Humans on Ecosystems.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 07:38:55 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib\media\pasted-image-20241118150252.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib\media\pasted-image-20241118150252.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Unit 1]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>I will have mindmaps for all units, unit summaries, full notes, learning statements and pastpaper questions. Unit 3 is mostly complete, I still have to compile the mindmap. Unit 2 mindmap is complete, but the notes aren't well done in written form and Units 1 and 4 are still a mess.<br><br><br><br>Photosynthesis and cellular respiration. Important key highlights are the processes of photosynthesis, the light dependent- and independent reaction.<br><br><a data-href="Photosynthesis" href="\unit-3\photosynthesis.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Photosynthesis</a><br><br><br><br><a data-href="Cellular Respiration" href="\unit-3\cellular-respiration.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Cellular Respiration</a><br><br><br><br><a data-href="Decarboxylation" href="\definitions\decarboxylation.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Decarboxylation</a><br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Cellular Respiration > 2. The Link Reaction" data-href="Cellular Respiration#2. The Link Reaction" href="\unit-3\cellular-respiration.html#2._The_Link_Reaction" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Oxidative Decarboxylation</a><br>
<a data-href="ATP Synthase" href="\definitions\atp-synthase.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">ATP Synthase</a><br><br>Annotation of a diagram of a mitochondrion to indicate the adaptations to its function.<br>
(<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Labeled Mitochondria Structural Diagram.png" data-href="Labeled Mitochondria Structural Diagram.png" href="\files-and-refferences\labeled-mitochondria-structural-diagram.png" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Annotated Diagram</a>)  CORRECTION : INTERMEMBRANE SPACE "PROTONS ARE PUMPED"<br><img alt="Mitochondria Microscope Image.png" src="\files-and-refferences\mitochondria-microscope-image.png" style="width: 300px; max-width: 100%;"><br>]]></description><link>index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">index.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2024 04:46:40 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="files-and-refferences\mitochondria-microscope-image.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;files-and-refferences\mitochondria-microscope-image.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>